<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Several short, but seasonable discourses touching common and private prayer relating to the publick offices of the church. By R. Sherlock, D.D. Rector of Winwick, and author of The Practical Christian.</title>
            <author>Sherlock, R. (Richard), 1612-1689.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 117 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 66 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59783</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3258</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221149</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832515</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832515</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36989</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59783)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36989)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2059:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Several short, but seasonable discourses touching common and private prayer relating to the publick offices of the church. By R. Sherlock, D.D. Rector of Winwick, and author of The Practical Christian.</title>
                  <author>Sherlock, R. (Richard), 1612-1689.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 45, [5], 11, [3], 13, [3], 16, [2], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for R.S. and sold by Christopher Skegnes, at the Golden Ball in St. Paul's Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes: 'Dr Stevvard's judgment of a private prayer in publick', and 'A discourse of the difference betwixt long prayers prohibited', 'Meditations upon our going to church', 'A sermon. Preached upon the Archbishop of York's provincial visitation at Warrington', each with a separate dated title pages, continuous register and separate pagination.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; with faded print and a slight loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayer --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Devotional literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:36989:1"/>
                  <p>Several Short, but Seaſonable DISCOURSES TOUCHING Common <hi>and</hi> Private PRAYER, Relating to the Publick Offices OF THE CHURCH.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>R. SHERLOCK,</hi> D. D. Rector of <hi>Winwick,</hi> and Author of <hi>The Practical Chriſtian.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>I will Pray with the Spirit, and Pray with the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding alſo,
<bibl>
                        <hi>2 Cor. 14.15.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>R. S.</hi> and Sold by <hi>Chriſtopher Skegnes,</hi> at the <hi>Golden Ball</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1687.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="table_of_contents">
                  <pb facs="tcp:36989:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36989:2"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36989:3"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36989:3"/>
                  <head>A CATALOGUE Of all the following <hi>DISCO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RSES.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>I.</hi> Of the <hi>Irregularity</hi> of <hi>Private Prayer,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>II.</hi> Dr. <hi>Stewards</hi> Judgment <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>III.</hi> Of the Difference betwixt <hi>long</hi> Prayers prohibited, and <hi>continuance</hi> of Prayers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>IV.</hi> Meditations upon our going to the Church, with ſome ſhort Directions for our Demeanour in the Houſe of God, touching ſome too-much miſtaken and neglected Acts of Divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:36989:4"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>V.</hi> A <hi>Sermon</hi> preached upon the Archbiſhop of <hi>YORK</hi>'s Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial Viſitation at <hi>Warring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="discourse">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:36989:4"/>
                  <head>The IRREGULARITY <hi>Of a Private Prayer in a Publick Congregation.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I Have ſent you herein my repeated and enlarged Thoughts, upon what was once the ſubject of our ſerious diſcourſe; wherein I would not at all diſparage, or in the leaſt under value the <hi>private</hi> prayers and devotions of any perſon, whether of the <hi>Laity,</hi> or <hi>Clergy;</hi> whether thoſe prayers be by <hi>himſelf</hi> compoſed, or by <hi>others;</hi> whether they be <hi>premeditated,</hi> or ſometimes <hi>ejaculato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;</hi> whether <hi>fixed,</hi> or <hi>occaſional; oral,</hi> or <hi>mental;</hi> for thus, and all theſe ways, every truly Religious Chriſtian prays, and undoubtedly finds the benefit, and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:36989:5"/>feels the comfort of ſuch holy breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings forth of his Soul unto Heaven in his private receſſes.</p>
                  <p>But that any Perſon, eſpecially ſuch who have entred into holy Orders in this Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſhould preſume to uſe any Prayers in <hi>Publick</hi> of his own <hi>private conception,</hi> whether premeditate, or extemporary, before, or after his Sermon, other than thoſe Prayers, which are by publick Authority allowed, and publiſhed to that end; I humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive (with ſubmiſſion to my Superiors) to be unlawful in ſeveral reſpects.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, <hi>Tis a diſorder and confuſion in the ſervice of God:</hi> For thus the <hi>Publick</hi> and <hi>Private</hi> Worſhip of God are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, whilſt thoſe <hi>private Prayers,</hi> which our Lord hath confined to the private Cloſer, do yet, contrary to his expreſs command appear in <hi>publick,</hi> and uſurp the place of his publick Service in the Congregation. The holy duties of <hi>publick</hi> and <hi>private</hi> Prayers, as they
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:36989:5"/>are diſtinct in their own nature, and conſtant uſe, ſo they are diſtinguiſhed by our Lord, and diſtinct rules preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed for the diſtinct and diſcreet perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of either Duty. Firſt, for <hi>private Prayer,</hi> Mat. 6.6. <hi>When thou prayeſt, enter into thy Cloſet,</hi>—ſpeaking in the ſingular number to every particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. <hi>Secondly,</hi> for <hi>publick Prayer,</hi> v. 7. <hi>But when ye pray, uſe not vain repetitions,</hi> —ſpeaking in the plural number to many aſſembled together: where, to avoid the Heatheniſh practice of much ſpeaking, or multitudinous words in Prayer, v. 8. a ſhort and moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Form is given us. <hi>v.</hi> 9. Thus then <hi>publick</hi> prayer being diſtinguiſhed by our Lord from <hi>private,</hi> we are thereby forbidden to confound them in their uſe and practice: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40. <hi>Let all things be done decently, and in order;</hi> not prepoſterouſly, and diſorderly, one part of divine worſhip undermining another, and the leſſer and more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularuty Duſurping upon the greater
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:36989:6"/>and more general religious Office.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> 'Tis not only a <hi>diſorderly,</hi> but alſo an <hi>unreaſonable Service,</hi> and ſo not likely to be acceptable to him, who is both the God of Order, and of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. And the unreaſonableneſs of this <hi>private</hi> prayer in <hi>publick</hi> will appear, by conſidering, That all prayers offer'd up unto God in publick, muſt be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly known, conſented unto, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed upon (which the <hi>private</hi> prayer generally is not) by all them that joyn therein. Upon which agreement (and not ortherwiſe). Chriſt hath promiſed his preſence, <hi>viz.</hi> to hear our Prayers, and grant our requeſts. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.19, 20. <hi>Again, I ſay unto you; If two of you ſhall agree upon Earth, touching any thing they ſhall ask, it ſhall be done unto them of my Father, which is in Heaven: for where two or three are gathered together, there am I in the midſt of them:</hi> whereupon ſaith the Gloſs out of <hi>Origen, This is the cauſe we are not heard when we pray, in that we
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:36989:6"/>agree not in all things, —For as in Muſick there muſt be harmony and agreement of voices, or elſe it delights not the hearer; ſo in the Church, an aſſent and agreement is neceſſary, or elſe God is not pleaſed, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will he hear the voice of our prayers.</hi> 'Tis this <hi>agreement</hi> in prayer that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominates our publick worſhip of God <hi>Common Prayer,</hi> becauſe agreed upon by <hi>common</hi> conſent; which doth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſe, that tis known to all, that all may joyn therein: So it was ever in the Church of Chriſt, the faithful knew what they prayed for; and this, not at the ſecond hand, from the mouth of the Miniſter, but before they joyned with him. So Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome, Hom.</hi> 6. <hi>in Tim. You that are faithful know, what things are to be deſired in Prayer, becauſe all Prayer,</hi> viz. <hi>that is in publick, ought to be common.</hi> Tis the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation of <hi>Ignatius, Ep. ad Magn.</hi> who lived in the times of the Apoſtles, and ſaw our Lord in the fleſh, <hi>That we aſſemble together in one place, and uſe one
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:36989:7"/>prayer common to all:</hi> For if the prayers of a Congregation be not known, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and agreedupon, then</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> the people cannot joyn therein, it being little leſs <hi>than the ſacrifice of fools,</hi> for men to ask of God they know not what, but wholly depend upon the Miniſters unknown expreſſions.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> A Prayer, that is unknown before it be offered up, is to an Engliſh man, though ſpoken in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> as a Latin prayer to him who underſtands no <hi>Latin,</hi> for they are both lame and maimed, and cannot ſtand with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſenſe, except they make uſe of that Crutch, which we ſo much blame in the Papiſts, viz. <hi>an implicite faith</hi> to ſupport them; and both the one and the other do equally tranſgreſs that rule of prayer preſcribed by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15. <hi>I will pray with the ſpirit, and will pray with the underſtanding alſo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:36989:7"/>
                  <p> Thirdly, <hi>It is againſt both the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and practice of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church of Chriſt:</hi> no footſteps there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are to be found in Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, but many Canons of the Church againſt it, whereof ſome are noted in the Margin.
<note n="a" place="margin">
                        <hi>Concil. Lc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odic. cel. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 320. <hi>Can.</hi> 15.17. <hi>&amp; ult. Concil. Milevit.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. <hi>An.</hi> 416. <hi>Can.</hi> 12. <hi>Concil. Epaunenſ. celeb. An.</hi> 509. <hi>Concil. Gerund. celeb. An.</hi> 516. <hi>C.</hi> 1. <hi>Concil. Toles. quart. Can.</hi> 2. <hi>Concil. Venet. celeb. An.</hi> 452. <hi>Can.</hi> 15. <hi>Concil. Bracor.</hi> 1. <hi>celeb. An.</hi> 562.19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20. <hi>&amp;</hi> 22. <hi>Concil. Vaſen, celeb.</hi> 442. <hi>Can.</hi> 5, 6, <hi>&amp;</hi> 7.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fourthly, <hi>Tis a tranſgreſſion of the Laws and Orders of this particular Church of England,</hi> and this accompanied with the breach of that ſolemn promiſe, which every Miniſter, lawfully ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, hath made; no man being admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into holy Orders, untill he hath at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted the <hi>lawfulneſs of the Book of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer, and promiſed that he himſelf will uſe the ſame and no other in publick,</hi>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:36989:8"/>ſubſcribing with his own hand this at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation and promiſe: ſo that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary practice in the uſe of any <hi>private</hi> prayer by any Miniſter of this Church, is a breach of <hi>Fidelity</hi> to the Church, and to the Reverend <hi>Biſhop</hi> that Ordained him.</p>
                  <p>Fiftly, <hi>Tis alſo a tranſgreſſion of the Common Law of the Land,</hi> which in the Acts of Parliament for Uniformity in Common-prayer, both old and new, enjoyns peremptotily, under ſevere penalties, <hi>That no man ſhall uſe any prayers openly</hi> or in publick, <hi>but ſuch as are ſet forth in the ſaid book:</hi> ſo that both in this and in the former reſpects tis an act of Diſobedience to the higher Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and breach of the fifth Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>I might adde, in the laſt place, the Non conformity of this practice with all other Proteſtant Communicants be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas, their Miniſters being neither fond of it themſelves, nor per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſuch a liberty by their Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors.</p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:36989:8"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>Object.</hi> But to ſolve all theſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, tis ſaid, A <hi>private</hi> prayer before Sermon is allowed, nay enjoyned by the 55th. Canon of the Church, which is called indeed a <hi>Form of Prayer,</hi> but therein the Miniſter is not bound up to the uſe of the ſame words, but may pray <hi>to that effect.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, But ſurely there is no man, that underſtandeth ſenſe, and is not blinded with prejudice, will ſay, That the form preſcribed in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons is a <hi>Form</hi> of prayer, but an <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation</hi> only to move the people to joyn in prayer <hi>for Chriſt's Holy Catholick Church, for the King's Majeſty, for</hi>— and tis moſt properly called a <hi>bidding of Prayer.</hi> And 'twas Mr. <hi>Cartwright,</hi> that Ring-leader of the Puritan Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in the time of Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> who firſt turned this Bidding prayer into a long prayer of his own head; and 'twas the very Engine, whereby he and his followers undermined the Common Prayers of the Church.</p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:36989:9"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> Becauſe the obſervance of this Canon was obnoxious to the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and exceptions of many, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired an abſolute Prayer in ſtead of that <hi>bidding</hi> Form, it was propoſed at the Convocation held <hi>An.</hi> 1640. that it might be ſo ordered, and accordingly there was a ſhort Prayer drawn up, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſing all the heads of the Canon; the which, notwithſtanding the confidence ſome had of its univerſal reception, was rejected by the moſt Reverend Archbiſhop, who judged it neither ſafe nor fittng to alter that Canon, which was founded on the Injunctions of <hi>Queen Elizabeth,</hi> and <hi>King Edward</hi> the Sixth, at the firſt Reformation; which ſufficiently evinceth the ſaid Canon to be no Prayer, nor yet lawfully to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, auduſed <hi>Prayer-wiſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, <hi>Tis a preſumptuous uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and affront upon the Church of Chriſt,</hi> for any man to thruſt himſelf upon ſuch a Miniſterial Office, as he is not by the Authority of the Church intruſted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:36989:9"/>and whoſoever acts the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> in this particular, becomes <hi>Independants</hi> the one having no more juſt Authority derived from the Church that ordained him, to uſe ſuch a private Prayer of his own in <hi>publick,</hi> than the other hath ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to preach, or pray in publick, being not admitted into holy Orders, nor lawfully called thereunto.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, <hi>Tis an Innovation in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> a new up ſtart practice, brought into the Church not above 70 years ago, and may therefore be reckoned <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter profanas vocum novitates,</hi> which the Apoſtle admoniſhed to <hi>avoid, even all profane and vain bablings,</hi> 1 Tim. 6.20. canting language, <hi>new words,</hi> and <hi>new ways,</hi> ſuch as are contrary to thoſe <hi>old paths,</hi> and thoſe <hi>good ways,</hi> which the Lord commands us <hi>to enquire after, and to walk therein.</hi> Jer. 16.16. And ſuch <hi>New ways</hi> are fitly called profane, <hi>quaſi procul à fano,</hi> ſaith the Commentator, <hi>Lyra in loc.</hi> becauſe far from the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or different from the words and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:36989:10"/>ways of Chriſt's Church, and contrary to the Apoſtles <hi>Depoſitum tene,</hi> in the following words, <hi>hold faſt that which is committed to thee,</hi> 1 Tim. 6. <hi>i. e.</hi> ſaith the Father, <hi>quod tibi creditum, non quod à te inventum;</hi> what the Church, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by thou art admitted to the Miniſterial Function, hath committed to thy truſt, and commanded thee to obſerve, hold faſt that, keep cloſe to that, not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing thine own fancy and invention to bring in what is New, which ever undermines the Old and true way of Divine worſhip.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, <hi>If a Call or command from God be herein pretended, though not allowed by the Church, yet in this particular they are at a loſs,</hi> except they pretend imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Revelation with the Enthuſiaſts; for there is neither command, nor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample in holy Writ to juſtifie this Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate prayer in Publick: We have ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Sermons of the Apoſtles upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, but no Prayer before any of them, ſo that this is an act of uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:36989:10"/>upon the Publick Divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, a preſumption to do that, which God hath no where commanded; nor the Church of Chriſt allowed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sixthly,</hi> Liberty being permitted for any perſon of what perſwaſion ſoever to vent his private conceptions by way of <hi>Prayer</hi> in publick, <hi>opens a gap to He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy and Schiſm in the Church, to Sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Rebellion in the Kingdom.</hi> For their private errors and deſigns being inſerted in their prayers, do inſinuate into the Affections, and more mightily inflame the <hi>People,</hi> than by any other way of perſwaſion whatſoever; Old Truths being undermined by New ways of Worſhip, and vain bablings, the conſtant Parents of errors in the Faith. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.20, 21.</p>
                  <p>Seventhly, <hi>Thus Separations and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, both amongſt Miniſters and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, are bred and nouriſhed:</hi> for whilſt one Miniſter, or gifted man (as ſuch are called) prays thus, and thus, and and another in a way, and with words
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:36989:11"/>divers from him: one ſort and ſect of men likes this mans way, method, and language, tone and geſture; another ſort is taken more with anothers way. —Hence, <hi>One ſaith, I am of Paul; and another, I am of Apollo; and another, I of Cephas,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.12. which is the life and being of Schiſm: the remedy whereof is to obey that moſt patheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal exhortation, <hi>Now I beſeech you Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, by the name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that ye all ſpeak the ſame thing, That there be no diviſions among you.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10. To ſpeak the ſame thing, and to uſe the ſame words in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick worſhip of God: or, as the ſame Apoſtle, <hi>to glorifie God with one mind, and with one mouth,</hi> is the way to avoid diviſions, and to take off the people from their partiality and fondneſs, in preferring one Miniſter before another, merely for their leſs or more eminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies in this unwarrantable way of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
                  <p>Eighthly, <hi>By this Private prayer, the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:36989:11"/>Publick prayers of the Church are implied to be imperfect and deficient; are ſlighted, nay contemned, and undermined.</hi> For they, with whom this way is in repute, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally ſlight, and ſlubber over the <hi>Common prayer</hi> careleſly, irreverently, and indevoutly; but to their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived prayers give all the advantages of ſeeming zeal, both in their tone and language, elevation of eyes, hands,— and no marvel then that the one be ſo much applauded by the vulgar, and the other ſlighted; eſpecially when they are perſwaded by theſe Enthuſiaſts, that Common-prayer, and all the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies in that celebration, are taken out of the Maſs-book; that they are but a dead letter, and the invention of man; whereas the <hi>private, conceived</hi> Prayer, is no leſs than the immediate influence of the holy Spirit of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> At leaſt they ſay, That Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers read in a Book have not that quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vigour in them, like to the prayer <hi>memoriter,</hi> and without book; the one
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:36989:12"/>ſavours of the deadneſs of the Letter, the other of the quickning Spirit.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> But in holy prayer it is not the words ſaid, whether <hi>written,</hi> or <hi>not written,</hi> whether ſaid <hi>within,</hi> or <hi>without</hi> book; but the affectionate Zeal of him that prays, That gives vigor and effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to this holy Duty; and where this is wanting, the fault is not in the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers themſelves, but in the perſons, that profanely ſlight and undervalue them the deadneſs they talk of, lies in their own hearts, which are not touched with the quickning ſpirit of devotion, in the uſe of thoſe holy and good pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. And whoſoever ls more affected with a conceived than a written pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, thinks ſure, that the one is more immediately by inſpiration from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven than the <hi>other,</hi> and ſo ſmels ſtrong of the Hereſie of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſiaſm;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Orationis ſublimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas ex parte oran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, non ex ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitate vel ſubtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate verborum, ſed humilitate &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votionis affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctu ejus qui orat penſanda eſt.</hi> Jac. Alvar. de inquiſ. pac.</note> I am ſure, to ſpeak fooliſhly and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinently, hath been uſually accounted, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:36989:12"/>called <hi>ſpeaking without Book.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> 3. There be many Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal perſons, and ſuch who both uſe and are zealous for the Liturgy of the Church, do yet uſe <hi>private</hi> prayer of their own before Sermon; the which ſurely they would never do, if they conceived it unlawful.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is done, tis confeſt, by many perſons of known worth and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity; ſome with good intentions, to win upon ſuch perſons, whom no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kind of prayers will pleaſe; ſome that their private prayer may be a Pattern, whereby their people may learn to pray in private: and for theſe reaſons, I conceive, this practice hath been, and is ſtill overlook'd by Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Superiors. But in the general, this cuſtom is continued through inad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertency, in nor conſidering, and deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly weighing the <hi>equity</hi> or <hi>iniquity, fitneſs</hi> or <hi>unfitneſs</hi> thereof; nor can the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:36989:13"/>of this, or any other cuſtom prove the ſame to be lawful. There is a great difference betwixt a cuſtom founded upon the principles of truth and equity,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſat nos &amp; praecipitat tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditus per manus error, alieniſque perimus exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plis: ſanabimur, ſi modo ſepare. mur à caetu.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca de vita be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ata.</note> and ſuch a cuſtom as is contrary hereunto, how plauſible ſoever. Many perſons alſo that are eminent in knowledge, and piety, in the general, may, through long cuſtom, and many examples, fail in ſome particulars through inconſideration.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> 4. Tis obſervable by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that variety of expreſſions, and change of Forms in prayer, do more work upon the Affections of the People, and ſtir up their Devotions, than one and the ſame conſtant ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Form.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw,</hi> 1. This doth more tickle the itching ears of the people indeed; and the itching of the ears comes from the corruption of the heart: And ſurely
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:36989:13"/>their devotion is very cold, that muſt be warmed by variety of expreſſions; the which in preaching may be commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but not in praying, except by way of private ejaculations, it being one great deſign of Exhortations, and moving ing admonitions in Sermons, to excite their Affections to what is taught, and exhorted unto: whereas holy Prayer is not the cauſe, but the effect and iſſue of devout Affections; and tis then on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acceptable unto God, when it comes from a heart replete with humility, compunction, fervor, and Divine love, which do neceſſarily infer foreknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Prayers we uſe, that they be ſuch, as whereby our devout Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions may be expreſſed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. It is generally obſerved by the Maſters of Myſtical Theology, and Spiritual Life, that there is a <hi>ſenſible Devotion,</hi> which begins in the ſenſitive Nature. producing tenderneſs of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, drawing often ſighs from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and tears from the eyes, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:36989:14"/>a ſecret delectation and ſweetneſs in the ſoul; with which many perſons are much taken and tranſported, as conceiving ſuch pleaſing delights in Prayer to be no other than the influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the holy Spirit of God. And yet this exterior pleaſure of a ſenſible De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion is not always a ſign of a
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Jac. Alba. de inquiſ pac. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>par.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>Sanct. Soph. Tract.</hi> 3. <hi>ſerm.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</note> ſound and right temper of holineſs in the ſoul: Becauſe, <hi>Firſt,</hi> many wicked ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate perſons may, and have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed the ſame. <hi>Secondly,</hi> it may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from the natural temper. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> from the vehement intention of the mind. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> from the mournful tone, cadence of words, and power of language. And ſuch ſenſible delights, even in Prayer, are ſometimes the inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuations and illuſions of the Evil ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, to puff up the ſoul with <hi>ſelf-love, vain-glory, preſumption in Gods favour,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:36989:14"/>and contempt of others.</hi> I deny not but ſuch ſenſible conſolations are often the influences of the holy and true Spirit, given us for our encouragement in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and divine Offices, in the love of God and obediener. But there is great diſcretion and humility alſo required in the uſe we make of them; neither are we over-highly to eſteem of them (as the Caſuiſt
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Conſolationes ſenſibiles quumvis non ſunt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiciendae, non ſunt tamen ſupra modum aeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandae: quia nec verae virtutes, nec ſolidarum virtutum effectus, nec neceſſaria pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>fectûs inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta, ſine quibus plurimi ad magnam virtutem, ac mentis puritatem aſcendunt.</hi> Jac. Alv. ibid.</note> obſerves,) <hi>Becauſe they are neither true virtues, neither are they neeeſſary inſtruments of proficiency in true devotion: for without ſuch ſenſible conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, many holy perſons have aſcended to a great height of virtue, and purity of mind.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſtrongeſt Devotions, and moſt, effectual Prayers, are ſeldomeſt atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:36989:15"/>with theſe ſenſible conſolations, and ſweetneſſes, which flow in upon variety of taking expreſſions; for a great Devotion is like a great Grief, which is not ſo expreſſive in words, as a leſs moderate paſſion: a leſſer Grief alſo is waſted away by tears and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, whilſt the greater is both more ſilent, and more laſting; ſo the leſs and more weak devotion of the Soul is breathed out and waſted in variety of language, but not the ſolid, ſtrong, and laſting ſervor. Such was the prevailing devotion of <hi>Moſes,</hi> when he <hi>fell down before the Lord,</hi> Deut. 9.18.25. and that of <hi>Hannah,</hi> when ſhe <hi>prayed in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> 1 Sam. 1.10, 11. Their words in their prayers were few, and low, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard; but their deſires and affections ſtrong and prevalent, as being not waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by much ſpeaking. And ſuch was that Devotion of our Lord in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and on the Croſs, when he poured out his Soul in prayers and ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with ſtrong crying and tears: <hi>Heb.</hi>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:36989:15"/>5.7. His words were few, but his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion great, and prevailing mightily; which devotion was neither begotten, nor increaſed, nor poured forth in a floud of language, and various expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>for he went away</hi> (ſaith the holy Ghoſt) <hi>and prayed, ſaying the ſame words. Mat.</hi> 26.44. So that ſettled and ſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Forms of Prayer may be expreſſive enough of the greateſt Devotion: nor is God more pleaſed, or the Soul that prayeth more profited by variety of expreſſions, though the exterior plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of a ſenſible devotion may be raiſed thereby.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> 5. But ſtinted forms of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er cannot ſuit with all tempers and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions: a Garment may as well be made to fit the changeable Moon, as one Form of Prayer to fit all men, or any one man at all times.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Tis true, that limited forms of Prayer cannot be fitted to every
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:36989:16"/>man's fancie and affection, eſpecially amongſt ſuch men where ſuch prayers are either ſuſpected, or coldly enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained: but they may be fitted to all mens <hi>neceſſities,</hi> though not to their <hi>cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſities;</hi> they may be ſuch as may ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently ſerve every mans <hi>duty,</hi> though not pleaſe all mens <hi>fancies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. Though they ſuit not with every man's particular <hi>condition</hi> in all circumſtances, tis no argument againſt them; for that would conclude againſt all Laws whatſoever, wherein tis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to make proviſion for all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular circumſtances and accidents that occur: tis ſufficient, that all Publick Sanctions do ſecure the publick Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and whatſoever hath influence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on publick Societies and Communities of men.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> 3. Every man's private Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, wherein he may be ſeparate from the publick, is to be fitted by his
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:36989:16"/>private prayers; and therein he hath li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to expatiate himſelf, and enjoy all thoſe fancied benefits, and ſelf-pleaſing ſweetneſſes, which variety and liberty can afford him; that which cannot be expected in publick prayers, which are of a publick nature and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, ſuiting with publick intereſts, the duties, and conditions of all Chriſtians; and providing alſo for publick Events, that are either probable, or can be rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally foreſeen.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> 4. There are many Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances relating to particular mens bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſes, that are not fit to be inſerted in the publick Service of the Church, or to be mentioned in <hi>publick.</hi> It is more ſafe and prudent to recommend many things unto God in general ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, than to inſiſt particularly and poſitively upon them, eſpecially in ſuch things as are temporal and worldly, wherein men are more apt to be poſitive, and expreſſive than becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:36989:17"/>Our bleſſed Saviour knew well enough the particular wants and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his Diſciples, when they begg'd of him to be taught to pray; yet he deſcends not to any enumeration of thoſe particulars, but gives them a Form of Prayer in general terms, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was for a publick uſe and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> 5. If any defects and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences be fancied in thoſe devout and accurate peayers of the Church, which have been framed and approved by the long experience of 1600. years, to fit all publick concerns, and meet with all neceſſary conditions, to be commended unto God in publick; how much more may we fear the many <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences, diſorders, irregularities</hi>— in the private prayer, though pretended to complete and fill up the emptineſs of the publick? The <hi>defects,</hi> and <hi>imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencies, tautologies, errors</hi> and <hi>blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi> of many ſuch private prayers are
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:36989:17"/>obvious to each mans obſervation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> 6. Tis further ſaid, that it may as well be ordered, that one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Sermon ſhould be preached in all Churches, and at all times, as that one common Prayer ſhould be conſtantly uſed, and no other.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. The Church does indeed truſt all her Prieſts, and Deacons to <hi>preach</hi> to the people, and by way of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to exerciſe their gifts for the edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of others; wherein variety of expreſſions are very uſeful to move, excite, admoniſh, exhort, reprove,— which are the ends of <hi>preaching,</hi> not ſo of <hi>praying,</hi> as before was obſerved.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. If the Miniſter chance to fail by impertinent, tedious, or any ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regular expreſſions in <hi>preaching,</hi> the matter is of leſs moment than to err in <hi>prayer:</hi> Becauſe, <hi>firſt,</hi> it is more ſafe to be bold with the people than with the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:36989:18"/>great Majeſty of Heaven; the people may pardon an indiſcretion, a rudeneſs, a miſtake, if any ſuch happen in a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon; but that boldneſs, or impudence rather, which ventures to offer up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God their miſtakes and undecent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, is not ſo venial, and eaſily pardonable. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Sermons to the people are but the means, not any eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential part of Gods worſhip it ſelf; but holy Prayer is a part and a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part of Gods outward worſhip; ſo that to miſtake and erre in the one, is but <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcretion,</hi> if not wilful; but to err in the other is <hi>impiety,</hi> and <hi>irreligion.</hi> A mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, a falſhood in prayer, is not a <hi>lye unto men,</hi> but <hi>unto God,</hi> Acts 5.4, 5. the great Sin for which <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphira</hi> were ſtruck with ſudden death. Which ſhould ſtrike the hearts of all men with ſuch an awful fear, as not to dare to utter any thing unto God, that may prove falſe, or be improper to be ſpoken; nor yet to go beyond what they are authoriz'd to ſay in publick
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:36989:18"/>by the commands of God, and of his Church.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> 7. Our Saviour prayed Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempory, and by the Spirit, and his Prayer (<hi>John</hi> 17.) was long, and no part of a Liturgy.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thoſe Prayers of our Lord, which are recorded, were not Extem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pory, but ſet forms, and parts of the Jewiſh Liturgy in the Temple; which might be proved by particulars, if it were not too tedious to be here inſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: And his prayer <hi>Joh.</hi> 17. was a private, not a publick prayer; 'twas deſigned indeed to a publick uſe and benefit, not offered up in publick, and with his Diſciples, though for, and in their behalf: and 'twas a prayer that was proper and peculiar to Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, as the only Mediator betwixt God and man, and ſo not to be drawn into an example.</p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:36989:19"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>Object.</hi> 8. <hi>Solomon</hi> pray'd in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple a <hi>private</hi> prayer of his <hi>own</hi> in <hi>publick,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 6. So did <hi>Hezekias,</hi> 2 Chron. 30.18. So did <hi>Elijah</hi> the Prophet, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.16. and St. <hi>Paul</hi> the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.36.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> All theſe prayers, with all others recorded in holy Writ, were undoubtedly the immediate dictates of God's holy Spirit, whereunto no man, without ſin and preſumption, may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, at leaſt not depend and relie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon. And as for St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s prayer, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.36. whether twas a ſet Form or not, tis not expreſs'd, nor yet many of our Saviour's prayers upon record, and ſo no argument <hi>pro,</hi> or <hi>con</hi> to be drawn from thence.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> 9. The Fathers frequently began their Homilies with prayers, and St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf began and ended his Epiſtles with prayers, and there is a prayer extant of Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> which he uſed before his Sermon.</p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:36989:19"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> But what kind of Prayers theſe were is not conſidered, <hi>viz.</hi> ſhort Collects, or rather Ejaculations, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploring the Divine Aſſiſtance, which they uſed not always before, but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in the midſt of their Sermons al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, when they treated of ſome high myſtery of Godlineſs, of other matter of difficulty, or were tranſported with more than ordinary zeal to the practice of ſuch of ſuch a virtue, or the eradica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſome reigning offence amongſt the people; as is frequent in many of St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>'s Homilies. And of St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> he, being a Metropolitan, might ſurely aſſume ſuch a power, to compoſe a prayer for his own uſe, which is not, nay ought not to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to every inferior Presbyter. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> becauſe he uſed a ſhort prayer, and this but ſometimes before his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, it doth not follow, That every green-headed Miniſter may uſe a prayer of his own private conception twenty times as long as the other, and ſo fully
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:36989:20"/>as far diſtant from the pattern which our Lord hath given us; which is alſo anſwer ſufficient to St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s example objected.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> 10. But St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> affirms the neceſſity of this Prayer before Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, ſaying That Queen <hi>Eſther prayed for the temporal ſafety of her Nation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe adventured to ſpeak before the King Ahaſuerus, that God would be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to put into her mouth congruous words. How much more ought we to pray for the like gift, when we are to ſpeak for the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal ſalvation of ſouls in the Word and Doctrine?</hi> Auguſt. <hi>de Doct. Chriſtiana.</hi> And again, ſaith he, <hi>When the hour is come</hi> (to preach) <hi>before he opens his mouth, let him lift up his thirſting ſoul unto God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is undoubtedly a lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble practice for every Preacher to pray for the Divine Aſſiſtance in his Sermons to the People. And this not only in
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:36989:20"/>the <hi>publick</hi> prayers of the Church, but in <hi>private</hi> alſo, betwixt God and his own <hi>ſoul;</hi> and this, as the Father di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects, before he opens his mouth in <hi>publick.</hi> And ſuch was Queen <hi>Eſther</hi>'s prayer in private, before ſhe publickly ſpake to the King; which makes rather againſt, than for the <hi>private</hi> prayer in <hi>publick</hi> for, and with the whole congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation. St. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> could not be guilty of any ſuch practice; for it was againſt his judgment, being himſelf one of the Two Hundred Fathers of that <hi>Milevitan</hi> Councel, wherein it was decreed, that <hi>no prayer ſhould be us'd in publick, but ſuch as were approv'd in the Synod.</hi> Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times this Father did conclude his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon with an Exhortation, conceived in form of a Prayer, <hi>e. g. Converſi,—Turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto the Lord God, Father Almighty, let us render him all poſſible thanks, beſeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him of his great mercy, that he would vouchſafe to hear our prayers, and expell the Enemy from having any influence upon our thoughts and deſires, words and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:36989:21"/>that he would increaſe our faith, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern our minds, fill us with ſpiritual cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and at laſt bring us to everlaſting happineſs through Jeſus Chriſt</hi>—which is not ſo much a Prayer, as an Invita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Prayer, ſuitable to the Form preſcribed in the Canon of our Church.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> 11. The liberty or <hi>private</hi> prayer in <hi>publick</hi> is the way to make an <hi>able Miniſtry,</hi> whilſt thus they are put on to exerciſe and improve their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial gifts and graces.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Tis rather the way to make a <hi>Licentious, Fanatick, Brain-ſick</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, and in proceſs of time no Miniſtry at all; for from this practice it is that ſo very many unlearned, unſtable ſouls, have taken up the trade, and proved as eminent, at leaſt as well approved of by the people for their gift of Prayer, as the moſt learned of their Tutorers therein.</p>
                  <p>And whoſoever ſhall impartially
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:36989:21"/>weigh, and without prejudice conſider it, he may obſerve, that this <hi>private</hi> prayer in <hi>publick,</hi> both in Church and at home, is the very life and ſoul of that Schiſm and Diviſion, which is ſtill ſo perniciouſly kept up in this Church: Tis hereby maintained more than by preaching, and diſputes: Tis from hence that Parties do call their Leaders <hi>Godly Miniſters,</hi> and themſelves the <hi>godly Brethren;</hi> the <hi>children that cry Abba Father,</hi> the <hi>choſen and familiar friends of God,</hi> from their over-ſancy and familiar converſe with God. This is that great Idol, whom all the world of Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts on this ſide the pale of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church adore and worſhip, crying down the goodly frame of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in his Church under the notion of <hi>Idolatry, Superſtition,</hi> and <hi>Will-worſhip,</hi> that every one may <hi>ſet up his Idols in his own heart,</hi> follow the ſway of their own imaginations, to be guilty themſelves of that <hi>Will-worſhip,</hi> which they falſly impute to the Church of Chriſt.</p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:36989:22"/>
                  <p> Upon this Rock many thouſands of Souls have ſuffered ſhipwrack, who have been otherwiſe piouſly inclined: For being taken with <hi>holy language, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious tone,</hi> and <hi>ſceming zeal</hi> of this or the other perſon in their private and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived prayers, they have in reſpect thereof ſlighted and undervalued even the Celeſtial Prayer of God the Son, all the divinely inſpired prayers of God the Holy Ghoſt recorded in Holy Writ, with all the devout and excellent Prayers of the Church of Chriſt, which are framed after the pattern preſcribed by our Lord, commanded by the higher Powers, uſed by the devout people of God in all Ages, and whereby many thouſand triumphant Saints in Heaven have pray'd themſelves into that bliſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful place of Eternal Glory.</p>
                  <p>After all this it would be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</p>
                  <p>That, as every error in Religion is very prolifick in bringing forth many
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:36989:22"/>others of the ſame miſhapen ſtamp and nature; ſo this erroneous way of divine worſhip, the uſe of a <hi>private Prayer</hi> in a <hi>publick Congregation</hi> is alſo productive of many miſtakes, and falſhoods, and deformed ways of worſhip in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement thereof: And</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Such private Prayers in <hi>publick</hi> are generally erroneous in the length of them: For that <hi>Long Prayers</hi> are <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful,</hi> is apparent</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> Becauſe they are prohibited by our Lord, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.7. <hi>When ye pray, uſe not vain repetitions:</hi> which cannot be underſtood of the ſame prayer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated, (which is falſly objected againſt the prayers of the Church) for ſo prayed our Lord himſelf, and his exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſurely contradicts not his Doctrine; whoſe Prayer, when moſt earneſt in his Deſires, was the ſame three times repeated, and a very ſhort prayer alſo, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.44. By <hi>vain repetitions</hi> then muſt be meant the repetitions of the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:36989:23"/>ſame thing in other words. For <hi>Firſt,</hi> to uſe multitude of words, and variety of expreſſions in prayer is <hi>vain, i. e.</hi> ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous, impertinent, and to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; ſince our deſires may, and ought to be expreſſed in few words, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent. <hi>Secondly,</hi> ſuch are generally <hi>vain, i. e.</hi> empty, and inſignificant, that have more noiſe than weight, more ſound than ſenſe, ſerving only to fill up the time, to amuſe the minds, and tickle the itching ears of the Hearers.</p>
                  <p>That ſuch kind of <hi>long Prayers</hi> are here forbidden by our Lord, is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> From the parallel Text quoted in the Margin. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Be not raſh with thy mouth, and let not thy heart be haſty to utter any thing before God; for God is in Heaven, and thou upon Earth, therefore let thy words be few.</hi> And this Text in the margin quotes another to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.19. <hi>In the multitude of words there wanteth not ſin, but he that refraineth his lips is wiſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:36989:23"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> From the cuſtom of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, as it follows, <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe not vain repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as the Heathen do.</hi> It was the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Heathen, ſaith the ordinary Gloſs out of <hi>Cyprian,</hi> to endeavour ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be eloquent, than devout in their prayers; and to be loud and cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous, rather than fervent and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous. And example whereof we have 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.27. where <hi>Elijah</hi> mocks the Prieſts of <hi>Baal,</hi> calling upon their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan Deities: <hi>Cry aloud, for he is a God; either he is talking, or he is purſuing, or he is in a journey, or peradventure he is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep, and muſt be awaked.</hi> And accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly they cryed aloud, thinking, as our Saviour here ſaith, <hi>that they ſhould be heard for their much ſpeaking.</hi> And therefore, as it follows, <hi>v.</hi> 18. <hi>Be not like unto them.</hi> It is a ſhame for Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in the worſhip of the <hi>True</hi> God, to be like the Heathen in the worſhip of their <hi>falſe</hi> and <hi>feigned</hi> Deities. Our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is, to endeavour more for humility, purity, and fervency in heart, than for
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:36989:24"/>glib, nimble, and voluble tongues; to pray, not with multitude of words, and variety of phraſes, but with pertinent and pithy expreſſions; with ardency, and godly zeal: and the reaſon fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows. For</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Your heavenly Father knoweth what things you ſtand in need of, before you ask him:</hi> He is every where preſent, and knoweth all things, even the ſecrets of all hearts; and therefore to court him with <hi>long</hi> and <hi>loud</hi> Peayers implies our ignorance, or misbelief of his perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
                  <p>Againſt ſuch extravagancy in prayers our Lord preſcribes us a Form, with command ſaying, <hi>After this manner tray ye,</hi> verſ. 9. <hi>i.e.</hi> as from the context is manifeſt, not after the manner of the Heathen, who think to be heard <hi>for their much ſpeaking,</hi> but <hi>after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, i. e.</hi> in few words, and ſuch as are pithy, and to purpoſe.</p>
                  <p>And, That tis the meaning of our Lord in this place, that all our Prayers
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:36989:24"/>ſhould be ſhort, and not much exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the length of the Pattern he hath given us, is manifeſt,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Not only from the Context im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially weigh'd and underſtood, but</p>
                  <p n="2">2. From the practice of Chriſt's Church, which is undeniably the beſt and ſureſt Interpreter of Chriſt's mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his words. And all the Prayers of the Church of Chriſt are, and ever were ſuch in all Ages, in all places, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all perſons that are called Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians: their Liturgies, or Publick prayers are ſhort and pithy, called therefore Collects, as being ſo many Collections of much matter in few words.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Such are all the Prayers of the Holy and True Spirit of God, which ſtand upon record in Holy Writ, both for uſe, and imitation, <hi>viz.</hi> the whole Book of Pſalms, with many more; all which, though ſome of them be long, as to the whole Pſalm, or Hymn, yet they are divided by Verſes into ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhorter Prayers.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:36989:25"/> 4. Long Prayers are not only for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden by our Lord, as the cuſtom of the Heathen, but alſo frequently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by him as the practice of the Hypocrites. <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.14. <hi>Mar.</hi> 12.40. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.47.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. By long and manifold ſad expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience tis well known, and hath been often obſerved, That all long, concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved prayers have been guilty of mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold infirmities; light, vain, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemly expreſſions, not fitting to be offered up to the All wiſe, All-glorious Majeſty of Heaven; yea many falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods, many impieties and profanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, have been uttered in ſuch kind of prayers, and what have been contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory to the Religious Duties we owe to God and men.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. If it be here ſaid, How can we be too long in our Prayers, ſince our Lord continued all night in prayer, <hi>Luke</hi> 6.12. and ſaith alſo, that we ought <hi>always to pray, and not to faint,</hi> Luke 18.1. and his Apoſtle commands,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:36989:25"/>
                     <hi>Continue in Prayers, and watch,</hi> Col. 4.2. and <hi>pray without ceaſing,</hi> 1 Theſ. 5.17. and how can theſe Commands be obey'd without long prayer?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> To this I anſwer, that there is a great difference between long prayers, and praying long. The one is unlawful, becauſe forbidden and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd by our Lord; the other is a Religious Duty, becauſe both com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, and practis'd by him: and therefore St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſaith, <hi>Oratio plus gemitibus quàm ſermonibus agitur, plus fletu quàm afflatu:</hi> And tis thus, <hi>The Spirit helpeth our Infirmities</hi> by quickning our Devotions, and inflaming our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires; <hi>he maketh interceſſion for us,</hi> i. e. as the ſame Father, ſecretly inclining our hearts to intercede for our ſelves, <hi>with groanings that cannot be uttered, Rom.</hi> 8.26. From which Text it is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent (quite contrary to the Enthuſiaſts ſenſe thereof) that tis inward groan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, not outward bellowings; the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal fervent deſires of the Soul, not
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:36989:26"/>multitude of words, which is the proper work of the Holy Spirit in prayer.</p>
                  <p>The ordinary Gloſs out of St. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> asks the ſame Queſtion: <hi>If we muſt not uſe many words in our Prayers, how ſhall we pray without ceaſing, as tis commanded?</hi> And anſwers out of the ſame Father, <hi>That both are to he obſerv'd in our Religious Devotions:</hi> viz. 1. <hi>That our Prayers be ſhort. And</hi> 2ly <hi>Frequent, and continued. So Chriſt hath both com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, and alſo exemplified in his Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Prayers. And St.</hi> Paul <hi>alſo; That our Prayers be ſhort, but often renewed; in few words, but with great devotion; ending briefly, and beginning afreſh; leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome intervals, or ſpaces of time for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>re-enquickening and enkindling the fire of fervor and holy zeal in the Soul. And its added out of</hi> Caſſianus; <hi>The Fathers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it moſt uſeful to uſe ſhort, but fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Prayers. To be frequent, that our Souls may cleave the more ſteddy unto God by often addreſſes to his Majeſty. To be ſhort, that we may quench the fiery darts
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:36989:26"/>of the Devil, who is moſt buſie to tempt us to dulneſs and deadneſs of heart in our Prayers; which he very eaſily effects, when the Prayers we ſay or hear, are long, and continued withont any inrermiſſion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Tis recorded of thoſe Primitive Chriſtians in <hi>Egypt,</hi> who were moſt famous for their tranſcendent Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and great Auſterities in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of Religious Duties, That their Prayers we many, and often, night and day continued; and yet, that they were ſhort alſo: not only in their ſolemn Aſſemblies, and publick Offices of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, but alſo, That their private Prayers were as ſo many Raptures, and Ejaculations, or Defires, darted up into Heaven. For, as the Father ſaith there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, <hi>bſit ab Oratione multa lobutio, ſed non deſit multa precatio, ſi fervens perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veret intentio. Let not our Devotions be accompanied with much ſpeaking, but much praying, ſo long as we can hold out in at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and fervency.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:36989:27"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36989:27"/>
                  <p>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> STEVVARD's Judgment of a <hi>Private PRAYER</hi> in <hi>Publick,</hi> Relating to the Orders of the CHURCH of ENGLAND.</p>
                  <p>With an Account of the <hi>BIDDING PRAYER.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by <hi>L. Lichfield,</hi> Printed to the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, for <hi>Richard Sherlock</hi> Bookſeller. In the Year 1684.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="epitaph">
                  <pb facs="tcp:36989:28"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36989:28"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Theſe are the words of his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, near the place where he was interr'd in</hi> France.</p>
                  <p>MEMORIAE <hi>RICHARDI STEWARD,</hi> DECANI WESTMONASTER. ET SACELLI REGII IN <hi>ANGLIA:</hi> Qui hoc tantum Monumento ſuo inſcribi voluit Epitaphium.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hic jacet</hi> R. STEVVARD, <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>I Aſſiduè oravit pro pace ECCLESLAE.</hi> Obiit 14<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Novemb. 1652. AETAT. LVIII<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="discourse">
                  <pb facs="tcp:36989:29"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:36989:29"/>
                  <head>THat it is not lawful for any Perſon, that hath received holy Orders in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to uſe any extem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary, or premeditated Prayers of his own private compoſure, either before or after Sermon, or in the Church in the publick Worſhip and Service of God, but only the Liturgy ſet forth and allowed.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> Becauſe it is directly againſt his own ſolemn promiſe made to the Church, when he came to be ordained; and that Promiſe is ſet down under his hand, when he ſubſcribed the three Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, (contained in <hi>Canon</hi> 36.) the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond whereof runs thus, That <hi>he will uſe the Service-Book preſcribed in Publick prayer, and no other.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> Becauſe the uſe of ſuch Prayers is directly againſt an Act of Parliament, <hi>viz.</hi> that for the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:36989:30"/>of Common Prayers,</hi> which enjoyns per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptorily under ſharp puniſhments, that no man ſhall uſe any other open Prayers than are mentioned and ſet forth in the ſaid Book.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> No man is to preſume to exerciſe any Office in the Church, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he be called to it, as it was in <hi>Aaron.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Seeing therefore both the Church and State have expreſly enjoyn'd us to uſe no Publick prayers, but the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, (except his Majeſty give leave up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on extraordinary Occaſion for the drawing up of Forms, which leave hath ground <hi>de Jure communi,</hi> both Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical, and Civil) it followeth, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Church nor State have given pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to any to vent themſelves in ſuch open Prayers in the Church, becauſe they expreſly forbid it.</p>
                  <p>To preſume then to uſe ſuch Prayers, contains in it a complication of ſeveral Sins.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Sin of Falſhood, or the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:36989:30"/>breach of ſolemn Promiſe; confirm'd by ſubſcription of the Church.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Tis an act of Diſobedience to the Higher Powers, and ſo it is an expreſs ſin againſt the Fifth Commandement.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Tis an act of Injury, and Uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion offered to the Church, in preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thruſt themſelves into a ſacred Office, which ſuch men are not to be in truſted with, nor thought fit at all to execute: for many many be able to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe unto men, (ſince if they chance there to fail in point of truth, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruity, the matter is of leſs conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence,) but the Church will but truſt but few that ſhall lead Men, when they ſpeak to God; becauſe there a Falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood may prove an abomination in Speech, an Incongruity may ſoon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to a Blaſphemy.</p>
                  <p>I would glanly demand of any pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent perſon, whether he conceive, that when the Church of <hi>England</hi> was in her greateſt glory, ſhe had ever in it 9500 Perſons, anſwerable to the 9500 Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:36989:31"/>that were able to lead the people in prayer? Sad experience tells us the contrary, and informs us loudly enough of the Soloeciſms, and Blaſphemies; and the ſame experience tells us, that their Directory helps them not at this dead lift, nay it may often prove the greateſt impediment, ſince were ſome weak men allowed as well their Matter as Words, they might perhaps come off with ſome tolerable approbation; but being forced to confine themſelves to matter, which either they well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not, or are not ſo well us'd to ſpeak of, their Prayers are oftentimes vain and ridiculous, or, which is worſe, erroneous and blaſphemous.</p>
                  <p>The licentiouſneſs of Devotion (that each private Prieſt durſt adventure to lead others in Publick prayer) breeding great diſturbance in the Primitive Church, brought the Fathers to decree thus, in the ſecond Council of <hi>Milevis,</hi> (where St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſate, as appears by the Subſcription) That no Publick
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:36989:31"/>Prayers ſhould be offered up to God, that had not been approv'd of in a Council; or leaſt agreed upon by the more diſcreet ſort of men. <hi>Ne fortè ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid contra fidem, vel per ignorantiam, vel per minus ſtudium ſit compoſitum: Leſt either through ignorance, or want of good pains, the publick Faith might receive hurt by ſuch Prayers.</hi> Now, beſides other hurts which the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath received by this unlawful courſe, all know that ſhe hath received one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable miſchief in the neglect and ſcorn of her Liturgy. For when <hi>Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright,</hi> the Puritan Incendiary, ſaw he wanted Power, either to extirpate, or to alter our eſtabliſhed <hi>Book of Common Prayer,</hi> he was the firſt durſt boldly uſe this forbidden Knell of Devotion; and thoſe that followed him improved it to ſo great an height, by poſting over our Liturgy with ſo much careleſneſs and ſcorn, and by giving all the Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to thoſe Forms of their own, both of the Voice, and of the Eyes, and of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:36989:32"/>the Hand; that the People began e're long to think, that the reading of the Liturgy was but an uſeleſs task im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd by the Church on the Prieſts; but that they compleatly ſerved God, if they came when the Pſalms were ſinging, becauſe, beſides that they ſerved God, and had the benefit of a Sermon, they heard a long Prayer alſo, ſet out with all the Devotion, and all the advantage that it could poſſibly receive, from the Art, or from the natural good parts of the perſon who compos'd it. So that he who will needs continue the uſe of theſe forbidden prayers in the Pulpit, takes the readieſt courſe (as much as in him lies) for the rooting out the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Liturgy.</p>
                  <p>I ſuppoſe, that theſe men do not at all like the courſe which the Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants now uſe in Prayer, who permit this extemporary or voluntary way, not only to the Prieſts, but to the Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and to the Mechanicks; and I ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine a main cauſe of their miſtakes to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:36989:32"/>be, becauſe ſuch an Office is intruded on by thoſe men, who have not juſt authority to perform it. But then, if they would conſider things well, they would eaſily find, that this uſe of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden Prayer hath metamorphos'd them into independants, ſince they have no more authority to compoſe ſuch Forms from that Apoſtolical Church that ordained them, than either that perſon hath, who is now imployed to make Shoes or that other Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtick, whoſe Formalities are a Belt, and a Buff—Jerkin. It may be ſaid perhaps, that many Churchmen both of great knowledge, and great place, have them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves us'd theſe forms of Prayer, and upon that ground why may not they? Truly, if to argue thus were concluding, it might ſoon free us, not only from the ties of many Engliſh laws, but from the obligation of the Decalogue it ſelf; which, without all doubt, is broken often enough, not only by thoſe of the common ſort but by men of great Place
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36989:33"/>and Knowledge. But we muſt diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh between <hi>Conſuetudo,</hi> and <hi>Corrupte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la,</hi> and ſo learn, that Uſages taken up againſt preſs-written Laws are <hi>Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> but not juſtifiable Cuſtoms.</p>
                  <p>One thing I ſhall adde more, and it is a ſhort Diſcourſe, How the Pulpit-Forms of Prayer were brought into the Church of <hi>England.</hi> We muſt know then, that in the time of <hi>Popery,</hi> the manner commonly was to uſe the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> or elſe an <hi>Ave Maria</hi> before Sermon; ſo that when <hi>Edward the Sixth</hi> came to compoſe his Injunctions, he made choice (as he had good reaſon) of the <hi>Lords Prayer</hi> for that purpoſe. But becauſe it was thought fit, that the King's juſt Supremacy in Eccleſiaſtical things ſhould be at the leaſt weekly publiſhed to the People, it was thought expedient to premiſe to the <hi>Pater no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> a Form (as his Injunction ſtiles it) of <hi>Bidding Prayer;</hi> wherein the Prieſt was not to ſpeak to <hi>God,</hi> but only to the <hi>People,</hi> exhorting them to pray in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:36989:33"/>for ſuch and ſuch perſons, but he prayed not to God at all, untill he cloſed with the <hi>Lords Prayer.</hi> This was likewiſe confirm'd in the Injunctions of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and expreſly call'd the Form of <hi>Bidding Prayer.</hi> And when King <hi>James</hi> of bleſſed memory turn'd thoſe Injunctions into Canons, his Law runs (<hi>Canon</hi> 55.) That Miniſters ſhould move the People to joyn with him in Prayer, <hi>viz.</hi> in this Form of Bidding Prayer; <hi>Ye ſhall pray for Chriſts Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church</hi> &amp;c. <hi>concluding always with the Lords Prayer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now let any indifferent man judge: Are Exhortations proper Forms of Prayer? Nay, let a diſcerning man conſider it well, and it will appear, that things there prudently ſpoken by way of Exhortation, and Narration, would prove very abſurd in Prayer. How fond would it appear, to tell the great GOD of Heaven of the <hi>Kings moſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Majeſty, our Sovereign Lord Charles, by the Grace of God King of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:36989:34"/>&amp;c. or, as ſome do oft tell GOD of ſuch a Lord, Earl of ſuch a Place, and Baron of another, and of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Honourable Privy Councel, and his very good Lord <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And yet when we do but exhort them to joyn their Prayers, ſuch Clauſes may not be unfit. I can ſcarce think of any other way to defend them; and yet tis true that this Form is there, viz. <hi>Can.</hi> 55. call'd <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er before Sermon,</hi> and ſo it is, becauſe we then ſay together with the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> to thoſe very purpoſes he exhorts. And they well know, who know Divinity, that all kinds of Prayer are reducible to that holy Form; but it follows not, that the Preacher's Exhortation is a Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, for that he then ſpeaks not at all to God himſelf but to the People. Indeed upon an occaſion extraordinary it is a Prayer of no ordinary compoſition, and therefore call'd the Form of <hi>Bidding Prayer</hi> both by a reform'd King, and a very glorious Queen, and yet <hi>de facto</hi>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:36989:34"/>miſus'd by an itching Puritanical par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; at firſt (no doubt) by Cunning, and Deſign, and afterwards (as verily think for the moſt part) by a miſtake of that bad end to which it drove; or by inadvertency of the Law. But it is moſt apparent, that ſuch forbidden Prayers are an eſpecial means to eat out the whole Engliſh Liturgy.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:36989:35"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36989:35"/>
                  <p>A DISCOURSE Of the Difference betwixt <hi>Long Prayers</hi> prohibited, and <hi>Continuance</hi> in Prayers commanded.</p>
                  <q>When thou prayeſt, thou ſhalt not be as the Hypocrites, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Matth. 6.5.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by <hi>L. Lichfield,</hi> Printer to the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, for <hi>Richard Sherlock</hi> Bookſeller. In the Year 1684.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="discourse">
                  <pb facs="tcp:36989:36"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:36989:36"/>
                  <head>A Diſcourſe of the Difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Long Prayers</hi> prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and <hi>coutinuance</hi> in Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers commanded.</head>
                  <p>THey who are true members of Chriſt's Church below, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to the glorious Saints in Heaven above:
<note n="a" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Exod.</hi> 25.40. <hi>Acts</hi> 7.44. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.11.</note> they do the will of God on Earth, as tis in Heaven,
<note n="b" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.11.</note> and that's un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly the way to Heaven: We cannot poſt bly loſe our way thither, whirſt we follow their ſteps, who are thither gone before us.</p>
                  <p>Thole Triumphant Saints in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven reſt not day nor night, ſaving, <hi>Holy, Holy, Holy, Lord God
<note n="c" place="bottom">
                           <hi>Iſ.</hi> 6.3. <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.8.</note> Almighty,</hi> Whereunto conforms the man after God's own heart, ſaying, <hi>O Lord God of my ſalvation, I have cryed day and night before thee.</hi>
                     <note n="d" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Pſ.</hi> 88.1.</note> Our Lord commends it as
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:36989:37"/>a duty incumbent, that men ought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to pray
<note n="a" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.1.</note>: and by his Apoſtle commands it poſitively, <hi>Pray without ceaſing.
<note n="b" place="bottom">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.13.</note> Giving thanks always:
<note n="c" place="bottom">
                           <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.20.</note> Praying alway with all Prayer and Supplication.</hi>
                     <note n="d" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.18.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>But theſe Examples and Commands are not ſo to be underſtood, as if we ſhould do nothing elſe but pray, which was an old Hereſy of the <hi>Meſsalians,</hi> and <hi>Euchites</hi>
                     <note n="e" place="bottom">S. <hi>Aug. l. de haer. I heod. Eccl. hiſt. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 10.</note>, long ſince condemned by the Church of Chriſt as being a thing impoſſible to pray without ceaſing in the bare literal ſenſe, becauſe this cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible body preſſeth down the ſoul, and corporal neceſſities do call for ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply: Neither yet, that we ſhould make long Prayers, which is the new error, and great miſtake of theſe times; the which, though generally the moſt uſed, and beſt liked, as being ſet off with the paint of a ſeeming zele, and pretence of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:36989:37"/>the Spirit, yet the unlawfulneſs of ſuch long Prayers will appear, if we will without prejudice and partiality conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that</p>
                  <p n="1">1. They are forbidden by our Lord, ſaying, <hi>When ye pray, uſe not vain repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions,</hi> Matth. 6.7. in which words our Lord means not, the ſame prayers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated, (as is falſly objected againſt the Prayers of the Church,) for thus our Lord prayed himſelf, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.39.44. where his Prayer was ſhort, and three times repeated.</p>
                  <p>And therefore undoubtedly, by vain repetitions in praying, is underſtood multitude of Words, and variety of expreſſions to the ſame purpoſe, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to no purpoſe; ſince our Deſires both may and ought to be expreſſed in few words and pertinent, according to the pattern our Lord hath given us.</p>
                  <p>And that tis the meaning of our Lord, when he ſaith, <hi>After this manner pray ye,</hi> that our Prayers ſhould be generally formed to the length of his Prayer pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, will appear</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:36989:38"/> 1. From the Context, if ſeriouſly weighed, and rightly underſtood; wherein is manifeſt, that the manner of praying by ſuch a ſhort Form, is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in oppoſition to the Heatheniſh uſe of much ſpeaking in Prayer.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. From the Parallel-Text in the Margin, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Be not raſh with thy Mouth, and let not thy Heart be haſty to utter any thing before God, for God is in Heaven, and thou upon Earth, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let thy words be few.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. From the Prayers of Chriſt's Church, which are in all Liturgies of the Chriſtian World, for the moſt part of the ſame length; and ſurely, the general Practice of the Church is the beſt Interpreter of the Scripture.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Such are generally alſo all the Prayers of the Holy Spirit of God, which ſtand upon Record in Holy Writ, [<hi>viz.</hi> the Book of Pſalms, with many more:] We meet with none that are of ſuch a continued length, as are in uſe amongſt us, but they are all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:36989:38"/>by diſtinct Verſes, into ſo many ſeveral ſhorter Prayers.</p>
                  <p>Long Prayers are forbidden by our Lord, becauſe ſuch is the cuſtom of the Heathen, [<hi>as the Heathen do,</hi> Matth. 6.7.] who mind more the Oratory and Language, Tone and Pronuntiation, than the Humility and Devotion of the Soul in prayer: and tis much misbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming Chriſtians to worſhip the true God, as the Heathen do their falſe and feigned Deities. And</p>
                  <p>Becauſe they imply a falſe notion of the Majeſty of Heaven, and a misbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of his Divine perfections; as if he were aſleep, and muſt be awakened, or did not underſtand our Wants and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, or, being otherwiſe imployed, he could not attend our Petitions, except in multitude of Words expreſt, and loud bawling for audience: So prayed the Prieſts of <hi>Baal,</hi> 1 Kings 18.27. and ſo ſaith our Lord of all Heathen people, that they think they ſhall be heart for their much ſpeaking; which is direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:36989:39"/>contrary to the true faith of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, who believeth and acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Omniſcience, and Omnipre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God; as it follows in the Eighth verſe, <hi>Your Heavenly; Father knoweth what things you ſtand in need of, before you ask:</hi> which Divine Truth is implicately denied by loud and long Prayers.</p>
                  <p>Long prayers are not only forbidden by our Lord, as the cuſtom of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, but alſo frequently reproved by him as the practice of the <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> who love to ſtand praying in the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues, and in the corners of the Streets, that they may be ſeen af Men, that they may be taken notice of for Godly men, deſiring rather to ſeem, than really to be Religious, loving the praiſe of Men more than the praiſe of GOD. <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.5. <hi>c.</hi> 23.14. <hi>Mark</hi> 12.40. <hi>Luke</hi> 20.47. <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.43.</p>
                  <p>To pray continually then, is neither to be underſtood of doing nothing elſe but <hi>pray,</hi> nor yet of uſing <hi>long</hi> prayers;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:36989:39"/>the one being prohibited by our Lord, and the other condemned by his Church; but in this and the like Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions is commanded</p>
                  <p>The intenſe Devotion of the Soul in Prayer: So our Lord expounds his own Command, that men ought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to pray, viz. <hi>that they faint not, Luke</hi> 18.1. to wit, for want of that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fervour and devout zeal, which is the life and ſoul of an effectual Prayer. And this ſame Celeſtial fire of holy Zeal in prayer, ſpends not it ſelf in multitude of Words, and much babling of the Lips, but is expreſſed in ſighs and <hi>groans which cannot be uttered,</hi> Rom. 8.8.26. which are truly the Breathings of the holy Spirit of God in prayer, who dwels not upon the Tongue, but in the Heart.</p>
                  <p>To pray continually, enjoyns the conſtant, and continued returns of this holy Duty; that we loſe no time, neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect no opportunity either of the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick prayers of the Church, or of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36989:40"/>prayer, and Cloſet-Devotions, upon the ſet, ſolemn, and accuſtomed times thereof; remembring, that the <hi>Time</hi> only, which is imployed in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Acts of Piety towards God, and Charity towards Man, is <hi>redeemed</hi>
                     <note n="a" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.6.</note> out of the all-devouring jaws of Death, and dark Oblivion, to be the Seminary of a bleſſed Eternity,
<note n="b" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.8. <hi>Mark</hi> 12.35.</note> 
                     <hi>when time ſhall be no more.</hi> Tis to this end our Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands us to <hi>watch and pray;</hi> by our conſtant prayers at Evening, at Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, at the Cock-crowing, and in the Morning, to watch for the coming of our Lord, to put an end to Time, and to all that is by Time limited and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſcribed.</p>
                  <p>That we ought always to pray, <hi>i. e.</hi> (ſay the Fathers upon the Text) at thoſe appointed Hours obſerved by the Church of God, both under the Law, called therefore the Hours of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and under the Goſpel, called the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:36989:40"/>Canonical Hours; ſo generally obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved formerly of all devout Chriſtians, that St. <hi>Hierome, [Epiſt. ad Euſtor.]</hi> with his <hi>Quis neſcit,</hi> takes it for gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that no Godly Chriſtian is either ignorant or negligent in the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch Hours, as being probably obſerved by holy <hi>David,</hi> or from his example derived, ſaying of his own daily practice, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.164. <hi>Seven times a day do I praiſe thee, becauſe of thy righteous judgments.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To continue in prayer, is to have our Hearts ſo inflamed with the love of God, as to be in a continual diſpoſition to pray; and this not only at all ſet and accuſtomed times, but at all times, and upon all occaſions and objects pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, to raiſe up our ſouls upon the Spiritual wings of holy Meditations, celeſtial Affections, devout Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies, and Ejaculatory converſes with Heaven.</p>
                  <p>Thus <hi>Enoch</hi> walked with God, and was tranſlated. <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.24. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.5.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:36989:41"/>Thus King <hi>David</hi> profeſſeth, <hi>I have ſet God always before me:</hi> Pſal. 16.9. And, <hi>I will give thanks unto the Lord, his praiſe ſhall ever be in my mouth:</hi> Pſ. 34.1. No time omitted, <hi>Evening,</hi> and <hi>Morning,</hi> and <hi>Noon-day:</hi> Pſ. 55.17, 18. <hi>Early and late,</hi> Pſ. 63.1.7. No place preter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; in the <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> in the land of <hi>Jordan,</hi> and the unbeaten paths of <hi>Hermon.</hi> Pſ. 42.8.</p>
                  <p>Tis the great and conſtant imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a true Chriſtian's life, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon <hi>God,</hi> to fix all our Hopes, all our Joy, and Conſolation; all that we can reaſonably deſire to enjoy condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing to our happineſs, both in this, and in the other world; in God alone, who is the Beginning, the Mean, and the End of our Being.</p>
                  <p>In the firſt and pureſt times of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, while the blood of <hi>Chriſt</hi> was yet warm, and more inflamed the Souls of true Believers, than in theſe later and colder times; then were the hearts of the Religious continually in Heaven,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:36989:41"/>by holy and Divine Aſpirations, even when their hands were imployed in any and every of their works upon earth. So the Divine <hi>Ephrem. Sive opereris, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve ſedeas, ſive comedas,</hi>—In all thy works, even in Bating, and Drinking, and Travelling, ſitting, going, ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, lying,—<hi>Pray without ceaſing;</hi> Take hint from every thing thon ſeeſt, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, taſteſt,— to lift up thy heart unto God, and refer all to his glory.</p>
                  <p>Tis recorded of St. <hi>Bartholomew</hi> the Apoſtle, that he prayed an hundred times in a day, and an hundred times in the night alſo.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ephrem. tom</hi> 1. <hi>Homil. de Orando De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um.</hi> So the great St. <hi>Baſil, Hom. in S. Jude.</hi> So St. <hi>Chryſoſt. Hom.</hi> 23. <hi>in Mat.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>St. <hi>Hierom</hi> profeſſeth of himſelf, that often on the tops of Mountains, and in hollow Valleys; and craggy Rocks, with eyes lifted up to Heaven, and flowing with tears, he poured forth his ſoul in holy prayers, and meditations. <hi>S. Hierom. Ep. ad Euſtor.</hi> So meditates
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:36989:42"/>S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> alſo; <hi>Te, Domine, mediter per dies ſine ceſſatione, Te ſentiam per ſopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem in nocte; Te alloquar</hi>— Aug. Med.
<q>O that I could meditate upon Thee, O Lord, through the whole day, and not ceaſe to be affected with thee in the night; my ſpirit ſpeaking unto thee, and my mind converſing with thee alway, and alone! Bleſſed are they, who think of nothing, ſpeak of nothing, but the Lord; who love no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing above thee, deſire nothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides thee: Bleſſed are they, whoſe Hope alone is the <hi>Lord,</hi> and all whoſe Work is <hi>Prayer.</hi>
                     </q> And ſeveral of the devout Fathers computed all that time loſt, wherein God was not in their minds, and memories: And there is great reaſon for it, as the ſame St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> meditates; For as there is no mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Time. wherein we enjoy not the ſweet influences of the Divine Goodneſs, and ſtand in need alſo of <hi>God</hi>'s protecting Preſence with us; ſo there ſhould be no time, wherein we
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:36989:42"/>have not <hi>God in our thoughts.</hi> Aug. in Marcum. <hi>Wait on thy God continually.</hi> Hoſ. 12.16. <hi>Seek the Lord, and his ſtrength; ſeek his face evermore.</hi> Pſ. 105.4. Thus St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and truly devout Chriſtians with him, have <hi>their conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation in Heaven,</hi> Phil. 2.20 whilſt they are upon Earth; and that's the way ſurely to have our conſummation in Heaven, when we ſhall be taken from the Earth.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:36989:43"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36989:43"/>
                  <p>MEDITATIONS UPON Our going to <hi>CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH,</hi> with ſome ſhort Directions for our Demeanour in the <hi>Houſe of GOD,</hi> touching ſome too much miſtaken and neglected Acts of Divine Worſhip.</p>
                  <q>As for me, I will come into thy Houſe in the multitude of thy Mercies: and in thy fear will I worſhip towards thy Holy Temple.
<bibl>
                        <hi>Pſ. 5.7.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by <hi>L. Lichfield,</hi> Printer to the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, for <hi>Richard-Sherlock</hi> Bookſeller. In the Year 1634.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="discourse">
                  <pb facs="tcp:36989:44"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:36989:44"/>
                  <head>MEDITATIONS upon our going to Church; with ſome ſhort Directions for your Demeanour in the Houſe, and in the Service of GOD.</head>
                  <p>UPon your going to Church, three things will be neceſſary for you to confider: 1. The Condition of the Place whither you are going, 2. The great End of your going thither, and 3. How there you are to demean your ſelf. All this you would conſider, if you were going to the Palace of an earthly Prince, who is but a mortal man, like your ſelf: and you ſurely have much more reaſon to conſider the particulars, now that you are going unto the Courts of the Lord's houſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt</hi> then, as to the Houſe whither you are going, tis indeed, as to its Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick, but like other houſes, made of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:36989:45"/>wood and ſtone; [even as the Lord's day is but like other days, as to the air and light of heaven:] but the rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive holineſs of this Houſe, and its emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency above other houſes, will appear by the Names whereby it is called, both in the Book, and by the people of God.</p>
                  <p>Under the Law, it was called the <hi>Tabernacle of the Congregation,</hi> i.e. the place of <hi>God</hi>'s meeting with his people; the <hi>Temple of the Lord,</hi> where he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents himſelf to the contemplation or view of his Worſhippers, ſitting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Cherubims as on his throne of State. Tis alſo called the <hi>Sanctuary of the Lord,</hi> the <hi>Houſe of God,</hi> the <hi>Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of his Holineſs,</hi> and <hi>the place where his Honour dwelleth.</hi> All which Names do explain each other, and need no In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation.</p>
                  <p>Under the Goſpel tis called <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>the Church of God;</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>the Lord's Houſe;</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>the King's Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace;</hi> and <hi>Oratorium,</hi> the <hi>Houſe of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</hi> Any of which Names (much more
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:36989:45"/>all of them together conſidered) will oblige any man, who hath any ſenſe of Religion, to obey that command of God himſelf, which is not merely ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonial and typical, but moral and perpetual, <hi>Ye ſhall keep my Sabbaths, and reverence my Sanctuary.</hi> Lev. 19.30.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> As to the great end of your going to Church, it is to preſent your ſelf before the Lord, and there to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore the great Majeſty of Heaven, from whom you have your life, and breath, and all things.</p>
                  <p>It is not to <hi>ſerve your ſelf,</hi> by hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this or t'other fine-gifted Miniſter tickling your itching ears, by his tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Diſcourſes agreeable to your fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; but to <hi>ſerve the Lord</hi> is your Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand to his Houſe, <hi>viz.</hi> there to joyn with the Miniſter, and the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in publick prayers and praſſes of God, in Pſalms, and Hymns, and Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſongs, in Confeſſions, Thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and Benedictions, as wherein chiefly the Service of God conſiſts.</p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:36989:46"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>Behold, now praiſe the Lord, all ye ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the Lord; ye that by night ſtand in the Houſe of the Lord, even in the Courts of the houſe of our God. Lift up your hands in the Sanctuary, and praiſe the Lord.</hi> Pſ. 134.1.2.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>As for me, I will worſhip towards thy holy Temple, and praiſe thy Name.</hi>— Pſ. 138.2.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> As to your Carriage and Demeanour in the houſe of God, you are commanded, <hi>Keep thy foot, when thou goeſt into the houſe of God,</hi> Eccleſ. 5.1. enjoyning thee, <hi>Firſt,</hi> to beware of all light, unſeemly, indecent, and irreve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent carriage, and to ſhew humility, and devotion in all the geſtures of thy Outward man; <hi>bowing down</hi> thy ſelf, <hi>and kneeling before the Lord thy Maker;</hi> Pſ. 95.6. before him, who made both thy body, and ſoul, and joyned them together, that they might be joyned in his Service. So worſhipped the people of God, the whole Congregation <hi>how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves with their faces to the ground.</hi>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:36989:46"/>2 <hi>Chron,</hi> 7.3. And ſo all good people reſolve to do: <hi>We will go into his Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, and fall low on our knees before his footſtool.</hi> Pſ. 132.7. <hi>Secondly,</hi> The <hi>foot</hi> of the Inward man muſt alſo, and chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>be kept</hi> upright in the houſe of God. Thy Affections are the <hi>feet,</hi> or moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of thy Soul: theſe muſt be kept free from all ſecular cares, pure from all ſenſual luſts, clean from all wantons wicked inclinations, yea from all thoughts of any worldly concerns; for <hi>ye cannot ſerve God and Mammon.</hi> Mat. 6.24.</p>
                  <p>In the High-prieſt's forehead was engraven in a plate of Gold, <hi>Holineſs to the Lord, Exod.</hi> 28.36. and every or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Prieſt was commanded to <hi>waſh</hi> before he entred into the Sanctuary; <hi>Exod.</hi> 30.19, 10. intimating that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act Purity and Holineſs which is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of all, both Prieſts and People, when we approach the preſence of the Lord in his holy Temple So ſaith the holy man of God, <hi>Holineſs becometh thy houſe,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:36989:47"/>O Lord; for ever,</hi> Pſ. 93.5. and he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves accordingly, <hi>I will waſh my hands in innocency, and ſo will I go to thine Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar.</hi> Pſ. 26.6.</p>
                  <p>Be not ſlothful and negligent, averſe and careleſs, backward and tardy in coming to the Church; for many and miſchievous are the conſequents of coming late. For 1. you rob your ſelf of the opportunity of your private prayers for a Bleſſing upon the publick. 2. You loſe the benefit of the publick Confeſſion and Abſolution, which are of high eſteem and value to all who are wiſely religious. And 3. to deprive your ſelf wittingly and willingly of any part of God's publick Worſhip, is both a ſin and a loſs of ſo great an account, as cannot eaſily be expreſt, nor will be ordinarily believed. Againſt ſuch ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſloth and neglect endeavour to have imprinted in your heart the love of <hi>God</hi>'s Houſe, and of his Service there performed. Say with the man after God's own heart.</p>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:36989:47"/>
                     <p>Lord, I have loved the habitation of thy Houſe, and the place where thine honour dwelleth.
<bibl>
                           <hi>Pſ 26.8.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                     </p>
                     <p>I was glad when they ſaid unto me, We will go unto the houſe of the Lord.
<bibl>
                           <hi>Pſalm 122.1.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                     </p>
                     <p>Our feet ſtand in thy gates, O Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.
<bibl>
                           <hi>verſ. 2.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <div n="1" type="action">
                     <head>I. <hi>When you come to the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>door.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>COnſider, that you are now upon entrance into the Preſence cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the great King of the World, whoſe <hi>Throne of Glory</hi> is in Heaven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, but his <hi>Throne of Grace</hi> in his Temple here below. Say then within your ſelf.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Surely the Lord is in this place. —</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>How dreadful is this place! This is none other but the houſe of God, this is the gate of heaven.</hi>
                        <bibl>Gen. 28.16, 17.</bibl>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>How amiable are thy Dwellings, thou Lord of hoſts!</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:36989:48"/>
                     <p> 
                        <hi>My ſoul hath a deſire and longing to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the Courts of the Lord: my heart and my fleſh rejoyce in the living God.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Yea the Sparrow hath found her an houſe, and the Swallow a neſt, where ſhe may lay her young, even thine Altars, O Lord of hoſts, my King, and my God!</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Bleſſed are they who dwell in thy houſe: they will always be praiſing thee.</hi>
                        <bibl>Pſ. 84.1, 2, 3, 4.</bibl>
                     </p>
                     <p>And moſt happy were I, could I both eſteem it, and make it my grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt joy, and conſtant labour of love, to praiſe the Lord in his Temple.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="action">
                     <head>II. <hi>When you are entred, and view the</hi> Baptiſterion, <hi>or</hi> Font.</head>
                     <p>GIve hearty thanks unto God for your Chriſtendom; that by holy Baptiſm he hath called you to the ſtate of Grace and Salvation through <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> and humbly beſeech God to give you his grace to continue in the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:36989:48"/>ſame to your lifes end, by the religious obſervance of that Vow, which was ſo ſolemnly taken in your Name, the which you muſt now perform, that you forfeit not the great priviledges, rewards, and honours, of being a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> a child of <hi>God,</hi> and an heir of the Kingdom of Heaven.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="action">
                     <head>III. <hi>When you view the Pulpit.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>REmember how many good Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons you have received thence; the which not being carefully practiſed, will riſe up in judgment againſt you in the great day of your Trial. Reſolve therefore, for the future, to be a Doer of the Word, and not a Hearer only, deceiving your own Self.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="action">
                     <head>IV. <hi>When you look up towards the Altar, ſay,</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>VVHat reward ſhall I give unto the Lord, for all the benefits he hath done unto me?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:36989:49"/>
                     <p> 
                        <hi>I will receive the cup of ſalvation,</hi> [of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the ſacrifice of Thankſgiving for my Redemption,] <hi>and call upon the name of the Lord.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I will pay my Vows unto the Lord in the ſight of all the people, in the Courts of the Lords houſe; even in the midſt of thee O Jeruſalem. Praiſe the Lord.</hi> Pſ. 116.12, 13, 14, 18, 19.</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Glory be to the Father—</l>
                        <l>As it was in the beginning—</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="action">
                     <head>V. <hi>When you come to your Seat, kneeling down, pray,</hi>
                     </head>
                     <div n="1" type="prayer">
                        <head>I. Prayer.</head>
                        <p>LET thy merciful ears, O Lord, be open to the prayers of thy humble ſervants: and grant that what we ask faithfully, we may obtain effectually, through Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="prayer">
                        <pb n="11" facs="tcp:36989:49"/>
                        <head>II. Prayer.</head>
                        <p>O God, for as much as without thee we are not able to pleaſe thee, grant that thy Holy Spirit may in all things direct and rule our hearts; and more eſpecially be aſſiſtant to us in all the holy Actions of this Day, through Jeſus Chriſt—</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="prayer">
                        <head>III. Prayer.</head>
                        <p>AND ſince by reaſon of our ſins we are unworthy to offer up any ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to ſo pure a Majeſty; grant, merciful Lord, both to me, and to all thy faithful people, Pardon, and Peace: that being cleanſed from all our ſins, we may ſerve thee with a quiet mind, through Jeſus Chriſt—</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="directions">
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:36989:50"/>
                     <head>DIRECTIONS relating to ſome parts of the Publick Worſhip.</head>
                     <p>AS ſoon as the Miniſter begins with the Publick Worſhip, all your Private Meditations and Prayers muſt be waved, and your Mind applied to attend diligently, and to joyn de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voutly in every part and paſſage of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Service; conſidering that this is the great end of your coming to Church, and your buſineſs there is to ſerve the Lord with your Chriſtian Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in Publick.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Therefore when the Miniſter ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts you, out of the Word of God, to confeſs and acknowledg your ſins and wickedneſs, harden not your heart, but with all poſſible humility both of Body and Soul ſay after the Miniſter in the Confeſſion of Sin: and to this, and to every Prayer, or other Act of Divine Worſhip, where tis preſcribed, neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect not to ſay, <hi>Amen;</hi> for that is, as it
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:36989:50"/>were the Seal to confirm to your ſoul the benefits thereof. And the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews have a ſaying, that, Whoſoever ſays <hi>Amen,</hi> with all his might, opens the doors of Paradiſe.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. After the Confeſſion, when the Miniſter comes to the words of Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, bow down your head, and ſay ſoftly in your heart, <hi>Lord, let this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don pronounced by thy Miniſter fall upon my ſoul, and ſeal thereunto the forgiveneſs of all my ſins.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. The Pſalms and Hymns are to be anſwered verſe by verſe with the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, that ſo all may joyn and bear a part in the Service of God: for, <hi>in his Temple doth every man ſpeak of his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</hi> Pſ. 29.9. And here, although you cannot read, yet your Heart may joyn with them that do read; and your Mouth alſo may ſhew forth the Praiſe of God, by ſaying after every Pſalm, <hi>Glory be to the Father, and to—</hi> or elſe, if it fall in couſe, <hi>As it was in the beginning, is now</hi>— adding always, <hi>Amen,</hi> to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:36989:51"/>how affectionately you deſire the Glory of God.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Be not ſilent, nor aſhamed pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly and audibly to make Confeſſion of the holy Chriſtian Faith, when you are thereunto called by the Miniſter; for this is a duty you owe both to God and Man; it is an act of God's Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and a Declaration that you hold the ſame Faith with all true Chriſtians: and therfore tis required of you, not only <hi>with the Heart to believe unto right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eouſneſs,</hi> but that <hi>with the Mouth</hi> alſo <hi>Confeſſion be made unto ſalvation.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And when the Confeſſion of Faith is publickly pronounced, do not you ſit, or loll, as if it concerned you not, but <hi>ſtand up,</hi> with the reſt of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, to ſignifie and declare, that you will <hi>ſtand</hi> to this <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly contend for it,</hi> as being the ſame <hi>which was once given to</hi> or <hi>by,</hi> the Saints, the holy Apoſtles.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. Be not ſo cold and careleſs in giving Honour to God, as not to bow
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:36989:51"/>at the Name of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S;</hi> for tis a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty poſitively commanded, and univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally practiſed by the Church and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God in all ages. And therefore give no ear to thoſe deceivable Criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſms, corrupt Gloſſes, and falſe Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, which are 100 frequently, but profanely, urged, to make void the Commandement of God, in the omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of this Religious Practice. If you hear any ſuch Allegations out of the Pulpit, deteſt them the rather, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Act of Religious Worſhip ſhould be ſpoken againſt in the place, where whatever tends to the honour of God ſhould be magnified and advanced.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. That you may not be tired with the length of Divine Service, conſider 1. the great variety of its ſeveral parts, as conſiſting of Prayers, and Praiſes, Confeſſions, Thankſgivings, Invitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Leſſons, Admonitions,— all of which are with moſt admirable Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and religious Wiſdom ſo orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and contrived to follow each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:36989:52"/>that ſo the ending of one, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of another, may renew and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enquicken your Devotion, chearfully to joyn in all.</p>
                     <p>Remember 2. whoſe Service it is you are a doing, and continue therein from the beginning to the end, that you may reap the Benefit of the whole Office, both of the Abſolution in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and of the Bleſſing in the end, and of the <hi>Amen's</hi> throughout.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:36989:52"/>
                  <p>A SERMON. Preached upon the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>YORK</hi>'s <hi>Provincial Viſitation</hi> at <hi>WARRINGTON.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Acts. 20.28.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Take heed to your ſelves, and to all the Flock,—</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by <hi>L. Lichfield,</hi> Printer to the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, for <hi>Ric. Sherlock</hi> Bookſeller. In the Year 1684.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:36989:53"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:36989:53"/>
                  <head>A SERMON PREACHED AT A VISITATION.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Act. 20.28.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Take heed to your ſelves, and to all the Flock—</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the context we have S. <hi>Paul</hi> upon his Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation at <hi>Miletus,</hi> verſ. 17. And the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation, as this which is now holden with us, is <hi>Provincial,</hi> all the Clergy of the Province of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> being conven'd by this great Viſitor, and appear before him, <hi>verſ.</hi> 18.</p>
                  <p>The Text preſents you with a part,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:36989:54"/>but 'tis the principal part of the <hi>Viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiion Sermon,</hi> or as I may rather call it, <hi>The Viſitors charge to the Clergy of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince.</hi> The firſt part of which charge is:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Take heed to your ſelves:</hi> To you my Brethren of the Clergy, is this charge more ſtrictly given, then to the Lairy: For to the people God hath appointed Paſtors who are commanded in the text to take heed to the charge committed to them: But who ſhall feed and guide the Shepherds, who ſhall watch over the Watchmen, or teach the Teachers? <hi>Ye are the ſalt of the earth but if the ſalt have loſt his ſavour, wherewith ſhall it be ſalted, it is thenceforth good for nothing, but to be caſt out and troden under foot of men,</hi> Mat. 5.13.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Take heed to your ſelves, is the firſt part of the charge, And ſecondly to your Flock: The order obſerved in this Double Charge, is the next thing obſervable, which is the ſame obſerved by our Lord himſelf, in his charge to S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and in him to all Paſtors of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:36989:54"/>Church, ſaying <hi>Luc.</hi> 22.32. <hi>When thou art converted, then afterward ſtrengthen thy Brethren,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> 21.15. <hi>Simon, ſon of Jonas, loveſt thou me,</hi> and if ſo, it then follows, <hi>Feed my Sheep:</hi> Implicitly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding all Paſtors of his Flock: Firſt to be themſelves truly converted unto God, and their ſouls inflamed with the ſacred fire of Divine Love, and then they may hope that their pains will be ſucceſsful for the feeding and ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Sheep of Chriſt: That rule of Righteouſneſs and Charity which is the ſum of the ſecond Table of the Law, <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy neighbor as thy ſelf,</hi> commands this order to be obſerved, To love thy ſelf aright in the firſt place, and then thy Neighbor as thy ſelf: St. <hi>Bernard</hi> thus beſpeaks every Shepherd of ſouls, <hi>Tu frater cui nondum eſt firma ſatis propria ſalus, cui Charitas adhuo nulla eſt, aut adeo tenera &amp; arundinea, ut omni ſtatui cedat, omni cradat ſpiritui, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni circumferatur vento doctrinae, quanam dementia quaeſo, aliena curare, aut ambis
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:36989:55"/>aut aquieſcis?</hi> And upon <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.6. <hi>They have made me the keeper of the Vineyards, but mine own Vineyard have I not kept;</hi> he ſeverely checks, and reproves himſelf, that he had taken on him the Cure of of other mens ſouls, having not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently cared for and cured his own: <hi>Et miror—I do much wonder</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>at the Impudence of thoſe perſons, that thruſt themſelves to be Labourers in the Lords Vineyard, whilſt their own Vineyard is over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grown with Bryars and thorns:</hi> The Leper under the Law was commanded to have a covering upon his upper lip, <hi>Lev.</hi> 13.43. <hi>ut non docere alios praeſumat</hi> — ſaith <hi>Heſychius:</hi> that no man preſume to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen his lips in the Congregation, for the inſtruction of others, who is himſelf infected with the Leproſy, either of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs or error: for <hi>non eſt cadentis ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um erigere. Plutarch:</hi> It is not for a man that lies in the dirt, to raiſe up another thence; not for a man that is a ſleep in his ſins, to awake others from that ſpiritual ſleep of death; That Proverb
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:36989:55"/>remembred by our Lord. <hi>Phyſitian heal thy ſelf, Luc.</hi> 4.23.18. chiefly appliable to the Phyſitian of ſouls, who muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin at home, if he will work any cure upon the Souls of others.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. But this is not all, for thirdly the Cure of a Paſtors ſoul, is a more diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult task; as being to be perfected in a higher degree, then ordinarily can be expected from any of his Flock: For as our office of Prieſthood, is more high, more eminent, more holy, ſo ſhould our Converſation be, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>— St. <hi>Chsyſoſtom, De ſacerdotio, As Angels above men, as Shepherds above their flock, as Maſters above their Scholars, ſo ſhould a Biſhop a Prieſt a Paſtor excel and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend the people in wholſom doctrine, and holineſs of life:</hi> ſo the great <hi>Gregory, Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum debet actionem populi, actio tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere praeſulis, quantum diſtare ſolet a gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge vita Paſtoris,</hi>— with much more to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>De cura Paſtorali:</hi> A book which was once tranſlated by the wiſeſt and greateſt of our <hi>Saxon</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:36989:56"/>King <hi>Alfred,</hi> and by him commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the Clergy of this Nation; and a happy Clergy ſhould we be, an holy Prieſthood, if the Inſtructions in that Golden Book, were well obſerved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Take heed to your ſelves and to all the Flock] and both theſe joyntly and ſeverally, <hi>To your ſelves:</hi> As to the Innocence and Holineſs of your lives, as becometh good Chriſtians: <hi>And to your Flock,</hi> as Shepherds and Guides of ſouls: Under the Law, the Prieſts and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets of the Lord are frequently called the Angels of the Lord of hoſts, <hi>Jud.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Mal.</hi> 27. And under the Goſpel, the Angels of the Church of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.10. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.1.8.12.— And as we read of the Angels on <hi>Jacobs</hi> Ladder, aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and deſcending from heaven, <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.12. ſo the Prieſts of the Lord ſhould firſt <hi>take heed to themſelves</hi> by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending with the Angels into heaven, having their hearts and affections, their meditation and <hi>Converſation in heaven,</hi>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:36989:56"/>Phil. 3.20. And withal <hi>take heed to the flock,</hi> by deſcending with the Angels from heaven, enriched with the word of Life, breaking unto them <hi>that bread which cometh down from heaven, and giveth life unto the world,</hi> John 6.33.</p>
                  <p>But this joynt charge is ſadly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn'd and perverted, by ſuch as take heed to themſelves indeed, but 'tis not with the Angels to aſcend, but deſcend, only groveling in the duſt, and wallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the mire of Luxury, Riot, and Exceſs, Pride and Covetouſneſs, the pomps and vanities of the world, and the ſinful luſts of the fleſh, which every one, even the meaneſt of their Flock, hath ſolemnly abjured, when by holy Baptiſm admitted into the Fold of Chriſt. By ſuch as take heed to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but 'tis not in a ſpiritual but car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ntl ſenſe; who will look narrowly to themſelves, as to their worldly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns, their Revenue and Income; but are to careleſs to the ſpiritual concerns both of themſelves and their Flock, <hi>Who
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36989:57"/>ſeek their own, not the things which are Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Phil. 2.21. Caring more for their Families at home, then for the Family of Chriſt, more for their bodily then for their ſpiritual relations, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding better for their natural heirs, then their ſpiritual ſucceſſors in their reſpective places: And in a word by all ſuch as mind more the Benefice, then the office, more the Fleece then the Flock: All ſuch do falſly wreſt, and wickedly pervert, this double charge of the great Viſitor in the Text: <hi>Take heed to your ſelves and to your Flock.</hi> To your ſelves, by being examples of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to your Flock; And to your Flock; as <hi>Shepherds,</hi> to feed and guide them, as <hi>Fathers</hi> to admoniſh and reprove them, and as <hi>Mothers</hi> to nouriſh and cheriſh them: For theſe are the four Eſſentials of a faithful Paſtor: <hi>Holineſs of life, ſoundneſs of Doctrine, Chriſtian courage, Chriſtian Charity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. To <hi>all</hi> the Flock] not to the flock at random, not to this, or that particular
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:36989:57"/>Sheep, that fawns upon the Shepherd, nor to this, or that Party or Sect, which agrees with his Humours and Opinions; but, <hi>To all the Flock</hi> impattially, and without Hypocriſie, and this firſt affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matively, to inſtruct the Ignorant, to ſtrengthen the weak, to confirm the wavering, to reduce the erroneous, to viſit the the ſick, to comfort the afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to bind up the broken in heart, to reprove the ſinful, and to reſtify againſt the ſtubborn and diſobedient: Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Negatively, not to break the bruiſed reed, and quench the ſmoaking flax, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.20. not to ſow Pillows under all Armholes, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13.18. Not to ſuffer them to ſettle with eaſe, and without reproof, upon the Lees of their ſins, and and the errors of their wayes: Not to claw the ſcabbed Sheep, and ſcratch the itching ears, not to tickle and foment the petulant humors of the Factious, not to pleaſe thoſe ſqueazy Palates, who nauſeate the ſolid food of Gods publick ſolemn ſtanding worſhip, under the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:36989:58"/>ſcurrilous name of Porridge, and for no other cauſe, but becauſe it is like it ſelf, ever the ſame, conſtant to it ſelf: Like the Glorious Sun in the Firmament, which ſhines every day the ſame; which renders it a worſhip acceptable, as being herein moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the Immutable nature of God, <hi>the Father of lights, with whom is no variableneſs nor ſhadow of turning,</hi> Jam. 1.17. But the Itch after <hi>novelties</hi> in the Flock, and the Itch of <hi>popular ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe</hi> or <hi>filthy Lucre</hi> in the Paſtor, whilſt the one ſcratches the Itch of the other; Hence the putrid Scabs of <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Hereſie</hi> in the Church, of <hi>Disobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> and <hi>Rebellion</hi> in the Kingdome, are engendred,</p>
                  <p>Againſt all ſuch ſinful Compliance, <hi>Take heed to your ſelves,</hi> my Brethren take heed to your ſelves, and to your vows and promiſes, Sacerdotal and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical, confirmed by your reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pective Subſcriptions to the Articles and Canons of the Church, to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:36989:58"/>of your Metropolitan and Diaeceſan, to the Approbation and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant uſe of the Liturgy of the Church, and of that onely in publick: In which laſt particular, wherein the greateſt part of Miniſterial Function conſiſts, I cannot but teſtifie in this Aſſembly, ſo much concern'd therein: <hi>That there is utterly a fault amongſt us;</hi> In that thoſe divine and excellent Prayers, and heavenly inſpired Praiſes of God, and that ancient and conſtant way of Gods worſhip in Publick, is by many too much ſlighted and neglected, by many irreverently and indevoutly celebrated, by many mangled and maimed, cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail'd, abbreviated, and by the Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of others implicitly vilified: And generally almoſt by all ſecretly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd; enervated and ſubverted by each mans private prayer in publick: The which private prayer, whether before Sermon, or at any other time in the Congregation, doth not onely ſecretly imply a defect in the Publick
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:36989:59"/>Prayers of the Church, which muſt (forſooth) be ſupplyed by mens private conceived prayers: but alſo, 'tis a diſorder and confuſion in the ſervice of God; for thus publick and private prayer are confounded, which our Lord Chriſt hath diſtinguiſhed and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to be ſeperately obſerved, to avoid Hypocriſie and vain-glory limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting private Prayer to the private Cloſet, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.5, 6. and for avoiding Tautologies and impertinent bablings after the manner of the heathen, he preſcribes a ſet form to be us'd in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, <hi>verſ.</hi> 8, 9. We are commanded when we call upon the Lord, to pay our vows to the moſt High, and then he will hear, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.14. But can any man think it probable, that God will hear their Prayers, who ſacrilegiouſly break their vows when they pray, by praying otherwiſe then they have vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and promiſed? thoſe promiſes alſo being agreeable to the Commands of Chriſt, and the orders of his Church?</p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:36989:59"/>
                  <p> And this undoubtedly amongſt many others, is not the leaſt cauſe, of ſo many ſtray and wandring Sheep in every Flock, of ſo many giddy headed and factious minded men in every Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, of ſo many ſeparate Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations or Conventicles in every Pariſh: one great cauſe hereof is the falſhood and treachery of the Shepherds, who in compliance with the noxious hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors of the diſeaſed part of their Flock, take no heed to themſelves, nor to the vows and promiſes they have made in order to the right and regular execution of their Function, in feeding of their Flock: ſo for the iniquity and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular carriage of the Prieſts, the ſons of <hi>Eli</hi> in the ſacrifices of the Temple; <hi>Men abhorred the offering of the Lord,</hi> 1 Sam. 2.17.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. But ſhould not the Flock take heed to the Shepherd, as well as the Shepherd to the Flock? The duty of the one to the other (undoubtedly is reciprocal, and the mutual Relation
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:36989:60"/>reſpectively binding. <hi>Take heed to thy ſaid</hi> (ſaid the Lord to his people) <hi>that thou forſake not the Levite, as long as thou liveſt upon the earth, Deut.</hi> 12.19. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 14.27. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.30. There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more plainly aſſerted and more punctually commanded in the book of God, then that the people ſhould take heed to their Prieſts, the flock to their Shepherds, eſpecially ſuch as are Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedox and holy, that they ſhould hear and obey their voice, and make their Application and recourſe unto them, in all caſes of ignorance or doubting: <hi>For the Prieſts lips ſhould keep knowledge, and they</hi> (the people) <hi>ſhould ſeek the Law at his mouth, for he is the meſſenger</hi> (or the Angel) <hi>of the Lord of Hoſts,</hi> Mal. 2.7. <hi>Haec ſunt initia haereticorum, ut ſibi place<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, &amp; raepoſitum ſuperbo tumore contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> Cypr. <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Epiſt. ad Florent.</hi> Hence the Riſe of Hereticks in the Church, when the people ſwelling with preſumption of their own knowledge, and pleaſing themſelves in their fancies
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:36989:60"/>and opinions, proudly neglect and ſcorn to ſubmit to their directions, whom the Lord hath appointed to be their Shepherds and Guides of their Souls: And thus even thus, the people of God fell into Idolatry, even that groſs and infamous Idolatry of the Golden Calf, when ſlighting <hi>Moſes,</hi> and overawing <hi>Aaron</hi> the high Prieſt, they commanded him, who ſhould have commanded them, ſaying, <hi>Make us God to go before us, for as for this man</hi> Moſes, <hi>we wot not what is become of him,</hi> Numb. 22.1.</p>
                  <p>When the ſame people were weary of the Government of <hi>Samuel</hi> the Prophet, and deſired a King, the Lord ſaid unto <hi>Samuel, They have not deſpiſed thee, but they have deſpiſed me,</hi> 1 Sam. 8.7. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon St. <hi>Gregory: Quam reverendi ſunt Paſtores optimi Sanctae Eccleſiae</hi>—how reverendly to be eſteemed are the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of holy Church, who whilſt they faithfully ſerve the Lord in the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their function, they are ſo cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly joyn'd unto him in the bond of love,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:36989:61"/>that the leaſt ſlight, diſeſteem or neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, that is caſt upon them, the Lord takes it as an injury to himſelf: So ſaid the Lord to his Apoſtles, and in them to their Succeſſors: <hi>He that heareth you, heareth me; and he that deſpiſeth you deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſeth me, and he that deſpiſeth me, deſpiſeth him that ſent me,</hi> Luc. 10.16. And this duty, that the people ſhould take heed to their Prieſts, is commanded under a ſevere penalty, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.8. <hi>If there ariſe a matter too hard for thee in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, thou ſhalt ariſe and come unto the Prieſts, the Levites, and that man that will do preſumptuouſly, and will not hearken un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Prieſt, that ſtandeth to Miniſter— even that man ſhall dye.</hi> And under the Goſpel alſo the ſame command is given, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17. <hi>Obey them that have the Rule over you, and ſubmit your ſelves, for they watch for your Souls.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But notwithſtanding theſe and many more commands, in the ſacred ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s of either Teſtament, yet is this Chriſtian duty ſlighted and generally omitted,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:36989:61"/>and eſpecially by thoſe who pretend moſt to the ſole Authority of the holy Scriptures, without any Relation to the doctrine and Authority of the Church in the Interpretation thereof: There being many amongſt us in every Flock; who preſume to direct their Shepherds, guide their Guides, and teach their Teachers; who if they teach not, preach not, pray not, as they would have them, and conſonant to their hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors and opinions; they will cenſure their doctrines, contemn their directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, revile their perſons, ſcandalize their profeſſion, and even ſnatch the holy Oracles out of their mouths, and ſeparate themſelves into Conventicles, where <hi>they may heap to themſelves Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers after their luſts, having itching ears, and they turn away their ears from the truth, and are turned unto fables;</hi> believing and delighting in lies, and vain empty pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſyings which profit not, as was fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told of ſuch, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3, 4.</p>
                  <p>And having mentioned Conventicles,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:36989:62"/>I cannot but add a word of the danger of them, not ſo much in order to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance of the peace of the Nation, leaving that to the Secular Magiſtrate, but in order to the ſeduction of unwary and unſtable ſouls into falſhood and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors in Religion; <hi>Verily, verily I ſay unto you, he that entereth not in by the door into the ſheepfold, but climbeth up ſome other way, the ſame is a thief and a robber,</hi> Joh. 10.1. 'Tis the practice of ſubtile thieves when they ſeize on the honeſt Traveller to drag him out of the high road-way into hedges and by-places, the more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely and without interruption to robb and ſpoil him; ſo the ſpiritual thieves, falſe Prophets, ring leaders of faction and ſedition, do more eaſily ſeduce, and robb poor ſilly men and women of the ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimable treaſures of truth and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, by drawing them from the open and Publick Aſſemblies of Gods people in his houſes of prayer, into By-places and lone honſes, where they may more ſecurely breath forth the ſpiritual In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:36989:62"/>ſow the ſeeds of Schiſm and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and whiſper their irreligious Treaſons, under the mask of Religion. In ſuch places they may to their advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage vent and put off their counterfeit ware, their falſe gloſſes, and miſinter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations of holy Writ, and make their Apocryphal Comments upon Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Scripture, making the Holy Word of God to ſpeak not what the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pirit of God intends therein, but what their factious ſpirits and wild fancies would have it: That there ſhould be ſuch falſe Prophets in deſart places and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate houſes, our Lord hath foretold, commanding all his diſciples not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve or follow them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.26. <hi>Wherefore if they ſhould ſay unto you he is in the deſart, go not forth; behold he is in the ſecret chamber, believe it not.</hi> St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> obſerves of the man that fell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thieves, and was robbed and wounded, <hi>Luc.</hi> 10.30. <hi>Si non deſcendiſſet—</hi> If he had not been <hi>going down from Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> the place of Gods Temple, <hi>to Jericho</hi> a prophane and common place,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:36989:63"/>he had eſcaped that ſad diſaſter: To teach all people to beware how they leave the place <hi>which God hath choſen to put his name there</hi> the Temple and houſe of God, to convene in any <hi>common or prophane</hi> By places, under pretence of Religion, and the performance of holy duties in ſuch places: 'Twas otherwiſe with the man after Gods own heart, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 5.7. <hi>As for me I will come into thine houſe even upon the multitude of thy mercies, and in thy fear will I worſhip towards thy holy Temple.</hi> And with him reſolves the whole body of Gods people, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 132.7. <hi>We will go into his tabernacle, and fall low on our knees before his footſtool:</hi> And not only this under the Law, but under the Goſpel, <hi>Mark</hi> 11.17. <hi>My houſe</hi> (not the houſes of men <hi>ſhall be called the houſe of Prayer of all Nations:</hi> Not of the Jews as under the Law, but of the Gentiles alſo under the Goſpel, and 'tis there e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in Gods own houſe, that he has promiſed to meet his people, to be in the midſt of them, to hear their prayers and bleſs them, To teach them his waies by
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:36989:63"/>his faithful and true Paſtors, and there (in a word) to diſpence all the bleſſed means of grace and ſalvation to them, <hi>Deuteron.</hi> 12.5, 6.11, 12, 13, 14. 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 8.29, 30. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.20. <hi>Luc.</hi> 19.46. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.20.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. But the grand excuſe of the wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring ſheep and the cry of many Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox alſo, is, <hi>The diviſion of the Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards,</hi> who being divided amongſt themſelves, do lead their flocks into ſev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eral divided wayes of divine worſhip: And the generality of the flock being not wiſe enough to know what way to take; or whom moſt ſecurely to follow, they hereupon <hi>heap to themſelves Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers after their own Luſts,</hi> and with the Schiſmatical <hi>Corinthians</hi> 1 <hi>ep.</hi> 1 <hi>cap.</hi> 12. <hi>verſ. Every one ſaith, I am of Paul, I am of Apollos, and I of Cephas, and I of Chriſt,</hi> one man, or Sect of men, liking this mans way of preaching and praying, another anothers way, and others none at all, but independently rely upon the immediate teaching of Chriſt by his Spirit. And thus Sects and Diviſions are multiplied.</p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:36989:64"/>
                  <p> This complaint is too true, and ſuch ſad effects thereof too evident, and if not ſtopt will prove bitterneſs in the end.</p>
                  <p>But would you know who be theſe divided Paſtors or Preachers, or Sect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters rather, the corrupt ſprings from whom all our polluted ſtreams of diviſions flow? They are ſuch (in a word) as firſt divide from the Church of Chriſt in general (wherein they all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree) and then divide amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, into particular Sects, and Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, wherein they all differ: There is <hi>but one body and one ſpirit,</hi> Eph. 4.4. one my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical body of Chriſt, which is his Church, and one ſpirit of truth, quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this is our body, and its members, and them onely: And as it follows, <hi>One Lord, one faith, one baptiſme, one God and father of all, who is above all, through all, and in you all,</hi> verſ. 5, 6. <hi>In you all,</hi> that are members of this one body, and quickned with this one ſpirit, <hi>and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour te keep the unity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace,</hi> which is the duty enforced
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:36989:64"/>from the premiſſes, <hi>verſ.</hi> 3. Contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then ſuch, that divide from this <hi>one body</hi> the Church, into ſeveral Sects and Factions, and (which neceſſarily follows) ſuch are not quickned with this <hi>one ſpirit,</hi> but each <hi>with the fooliſh Prophets follow their own ſpirit,</hi> Ezek. 13.3. which the miſtake and miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>term the Spirit of God; ſuch as worſhip, not this <hi>one Lord,</hi> as we are all commanded, with <hi>one mouth</hi> and with <hi>one mind,</hi> Rom 15.6. Such as hold not the Articles of this <hi>one faith,</hi> with one joynt unanimous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of truth; <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the unity of which faith, till we all come, we cannot be perfect men in Chriſt Jeſus: but are like children toſsed to and fro, and carried about with every wind of doctrine,</hi> Eph. 4.13, 14. Such are all falſe Prophets, treacherous Shepherds, or in the Language of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 Corin. 11.13, 14. <hi>Such are all falſe Apoſtles; deceitful workers, transforming themſelves into the Apoſtles of Chriſt, and no marvel, for Satan himſelf is transform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into an Angel of Light:</hi> I may call them according to the metaphor of the text,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:36989:65"/>The Bellweathers of the Flock, the Ringleaders of thoſe numerous Sects, and daily increaſing diviſions amongſt us.</p>
                  <p>And although each ſect and diviſion muſt neceſſarily be falſe and erroneous, becauſe there is but one Truth, and one true way of Divine worſhip, which is ever conſtant to it ſelf, yet hath each di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion it numerous followers of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided Flock: as ſilly ſheep when a gap is opened, follow one another to the breach to ſtray from their Paſture: So flock the people (if not reſtrained) into the ways of diviſion and error, if any Sect-maſter but open a gap, and lead them the by ways of ſtraying from the Sheepfold of Chriſt, which is his Church. For ſuch alas, is the ſad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of mans corrupted and depraved mind, as naturally to be more affected with error, then with the Truth; more prone to believe lies, and more zealous in the maintenance of falſhood, then to believe and maintain the Truth: 'Twas ever ſo, <hi>When the Prophets propheſie falſly,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:36989:65"/>the people love to have it ſo,</hi> Jer. 5. <hi>ult.</hi> but a ſad queſtion follows, <hi>What will ye do in the end thereof?</hi> When the Prophets propheſie Lies, or (which is the ſame) do make and foment diviſions, and the people withal are affected with their lying propheſies, and ſide with them in their reſpective diviſions: 'tis eaſie then to propheſie and foretell the end there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to be ruine and confuſion: <hi>If a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom be divided againſt it ſelf, that kingdom cannot ſtand, and if a houſe be divided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it ſelf, that houſe cannot ſtand,</hi> Mat. 3.24, 25. Not the houſe of God, not the family of Chriſt, in what Kingdom and Nation ſoever eſtabliſhed: All the Kingdoms and Nations in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom, ancient and modern, from the firſt to theſe laſt and worſt of times, have felt, by ſad experience, the bitter effects of diviſions and errors in Religion; and none more than our own, ſo lately bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; even to the laſt gaſp of death, and almoſt buryed in her own confuſions; which took beginning from the prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſying of Lies, and overſpreading of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:36989:66"/>and errors in Religion, ſowing the Seeds of Schiſm, Faction and Sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in ſeparate and divided meetings, or Conventicles in private; joy ned with a ſacrilegious vow-breaking performance of holy duties in Publick. All which now are as much, if not more practiſed then ever; ſome of whoſe Factors and Followers, do really <hi>intend,</hi> all do cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly <hi>tend</hi> to involve this Church and Kingdom, into the fad condition of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtine war, blood and Confuſion, from whence by the great mercy of God, we ſo lately eſcaped.</p>
                  <p>And now to you, the Reverend per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who are come to viſit us in our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempers and infirmities, to you it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belongs, as much as in you lies, to give ſtop to our overflowing diviſions: To re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain our licentious exorbitancies, both in doctrine and practice, in Praying and Preaching, and this, whether in the houſe of God, or in the houſes of men: <hi>Et fiat Juſtitia, ruat coelum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36989:66"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
